by spirits, angels, demons, and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison
of a flat, secular materialism,
to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen DeYoung, host this live Colin show,
focused on enchantment.
in creation, the union of the scene and unseen as made by God,
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
A good evening, dragon slayers, giant killers,
mobs of the Magisterial 1962 Alfred Newman soundtrack
to How the West Was One.
You're listening to the 133rd episode
of Lord of Spirits podcast.
And I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick.
And with me is the talk of Twitter.
Father Steven
young himself, which is impressive since I'm not on Twitter. I know. I know I rent free
and all that talking about right in front of my face behind my back. We're live. The great
gatekeeper Mike purgatory old bed pan again. We'll be taking your calls tonight beginning
in the second half. The other day my brother sent to me a a D M and he told me that he's
not in Colorado, which he used to work.
And I think the company he works for now is still there,
although he lives in another state.
And he was having dinner with one of his former coworkers.
And a guy that he worked with years ago,
and apparently this fellow told him that he,
he and his wife, his family had converted
to Orthodox Christianity recently,
and that they were fans of this particular...
show and my brother's saying they're listening and talking about this and he goes so you know
that that guy on that show is my brother right and apparently somehow this fellow had never
put two and two together that he only knew two people with the name Damick. So anyway Eric
Sexton. He lived in a Lithuanian community of some sort. I know I know Eric Sexton Colorado.
So what's wrong?
with you. I mean, he's my just kidding. Very nice of you to listen to this.
There's good like straight casey case. I'm long distance.
Dedications now. Exactly. Exactly. Exactly. So tonight, though, we have a very special
treat, an entirely uncontroversial episode with zero spicy takes from Father Stephen.
This episode is designed to ease you into great length, detach you from all the cares of this world,
and calm your troubled soul.
that said, I'm going to go ahead and get all of the objections out of the way now.
So number one, Father Stephen, you're being unfair.
You're just mean.
You haven't really read everything.
You don't understand.
You're making caricatures.
You are a modernist.
You're warring against the saints.
That's my favorite one.
Did I miss any?
Yes.
We're talking about the internet and someone might hear this outside of North America.
Oh, that's right.
We're teaching outside of our diocese.
teaching outside of your diocese.
So just just to clarify that, if you're in North America, you must slavishly obey everything
we say on this program.
But if you are, you're inside our archdiocese.
If you're on any other continent, or even in Mexico or Central America, you could freely
ignore everything we say.
What about those unclaimed regions of Antarctica?
Yeah, so there's some dodgy things like Puerto Rico I think.
technically is it a different archdiocese and stuff like that is true even though it's technically part of the North America
It's part of the United States. So yeah, there's there's some nitty-gritty here people
If you're on the edge just disregard
Let's go do something else with your evening
But if you're in the continuous United States or a Canadian province, this is the law of the needs and the Persians
There's no escape for you.
That's how it works, right?
That's right.
Bringing it pause.
So, we're talking about Latin theology.
Yes, which is obviously going to be non-controversial.
I know.
Yeah.
I'm ready.
Yes.
Our last episode was a big hit,
and really reached abroad.
Everyone loved it.
A special
those people out there who believe that penal substitutionary atonement, which is a heresy,
Orthodox Christian doctor is a thing. Yes. I know. Yeah. Well, they're they're going to love this
one. Yes. Been more. But I am unfair and I am mean. I should also confirm by that. Yes,
can confirm. Yes, I will hurt people emotionally with my words.
And I'm under a patent about it.
And I haven't read everything.
That is true.
That is.
I have not read everything.
There are a vast array of products sold at stores in the United States.
I have not read their nutrition facts labels.
My youngest son by the way is on this, his sister who is 10 years older than he is, showed
him a documentary about processed food.
And now like if anything is like ultra highly processed or whatever, he'll just refuse to eat it.
So I were thinking when you mentioned that I was triggered, you know?
Yeah, see I get triggered the exact opposite way.
Like when I watched Super size of me, like I was craving a big man.
Like seriously, like that scene with dancing Ronald McDonald where they play pusher man,
I was like, man, I got to get to the drive through like now I'm pausing the movie.
So yeah, but that's not what we're pushing today. See, that's a segue. Great.
We're talking about Latin theology. Ed's will start with, why are we, why are we talking about Latin
theology instead of Western theology or the Western, Western Christianity or one of those things?
Yeah. And the reason for that
several if you're a long time.
to the show, you know about my very popular take that the West is a false construct. The
West, the way it's talked about, or Western civilization is kind of nonsense in that there
is not really a narrative through line that begins an ancient sumer and ends with post-World
World War II United States Global Hegemon.
That is no more a real thing than 19th century German
Pratges were a real thing
To be the pittacle of human civilization
But there's there's sort of more problems with it than that
What is an isn't part of the West?
It's kind of arbitrary and selective depending on what's being talked about so
So when you get that western-sive narrative that starts at the...
Sumer, obviously we want to claim all of ancient Greece, right, philosophy, democracy, all
that kind of stuff.
You would agree mythology a little bit in a watered-down version.
But then like, after that Greece isn't part of the West anymore.
It moved out.
The West moved on.
Russia like sometimes is and sometimes isn't right in the western
narrative, like it pops up a few times, like you read about the Bolshevik Revolution and stuff,
a Russian involvement World War One and Two, you know, and then it's out. And so if you try
to then apply that narrative to like what is Western and Eastern theology that it gets super
confused. So it's like when did Greek theology? Like obviously the New Testament is written in Greek,
So apostolic Greek
theology is born of Western theology, I guess, and then, you know, they kind of like the
capadocious and stuff, and then there's some nebulous point where all of a sudden it stops
being Western theology and starts being Eastern theology. And same thing, racialized.
And so it's not super helpful. And plus, people who use this narrative of the West, especially
the people who want to save it or something.
Their narrative always
involves kind of saving it from himself.
Yeah, it's some usually earlier version of quote, unquote,
the West that need to be saved from the later version of the
same thing that it evolved into. Yeah. So like the enlightenment,
some people want to cut it off before the enlightenment or before
the Renaissance. Some people will accept the enlightenment because
they like America and they want to include the founding fathers and
stuff so they'll include some of the enlightenment stuff.
they want to stop it after that. They definitely don't want to include like Karl Marx who lived in like
Germany and England
in the West, right? Like we don't want him. He's clearly not even though again, he's a Higgyalian,
right? Like he's Karl Marx stands in this through line, right? So like all of these things are Western
phenomena from which the West needs to be saved according to this narrative.
also very confused, right? And that's going to fold over as we see, we're going to see later tonight,
that those like philosophical names, for example, are going to fold over into
fee a lot, Latin theological movements. Yeah, right. So
so all of that makes the West
or West.
Christianity or Western theology, not the right adjective, right to use. Whereas, when we're talking about Latin theology, right, this seems to be a much more descriptive term, make sense to describe the set of phenomena we're going to be describing the genealogy we're going to lay out tonight.
So our geology is really going to start with
What are
Essentially Greek concepts, Christian concepts expressed in Greek, we should say, being translated
into Latin.
And that's both for the Western Europe, but also Western North Africa, well, that is still
a Christian thing before the Islamic conquest.
And so it covers that layer, right?
But also once it is separate, Latin theology is a very good descriptor for Roman Catholicism,
because before Vatican II, it's all being done in Latin.
And even afterwards, it's Latin terminology and everything that is set the stage.
And even in Protestantism, though Protestantism,
presents today, shall we say,
especially evangelicals today,
do not have a strong identification with Latin.
Yeah.
Not only are all the theological terms
for the Reformation like justification,
sanctification, glorification, all Latin terms, right?
Yeah.
But I mean Calvin wrote his institutes in Latin.
He wrote a commentary on the Latin vulga.
right like
Latin was the language used by scholars and theologians,
Protestant theologians for centuries, right, after
the Protestant Reformation.
So for all those reasons describing it,
this sort of throughline is Latin theology,
even though after the first half of the 20th century
less and less of it is in Latin per se,
Uh, seems
to be a better descriptor and to distinguish it from theology that's going on in, for example,
Greek and Slavic circles without... Now there includes anything we don't want to include,
nor excludes anything we don't want to exclude. So that's what we're talking about Latin theology.
That's why we're using those terms.
And so as we...
said, Latin theology per se begins with Latin translation. Right? And by Latin translation,
I'm not just talking about, though this is included, I'm not just talking about translating
the Bible into Latin, translating the liturgy into Latin. Those kinds of translation of actual
Greek Christian texts if
into Latin. But also the translation of theology into Latin. We've talked before on the
show about how the correct way to understand what's going on at the ecumenical councils
with terms like Homo Ucius and these kind of things is that biblical concepts, often concepts
that started out in Hebrew or Aramaic are being, the concept itself is being translated,
video.
a label from a new language is being applied to that concept. So that that label, that word
could be used as a descriptor to describe a concept that already existed within Christian
theology. And so the same thing is going to happen in the transition from Greek to Latin.
So the terminology of nature per-
and those are both Latin words, by the way.
Essence, right? All of these things are going to get shifted from the original Greek term to a Latin term.
And this happens beginning at the very end, like the last decade of the second century,
an effort toward this starts to be made in the West because at that point,
And
there in a situation where the only place where Greek was being used commonly in Western
Europe and Christian North Africa was in Christian circles and in the liturgy.
Yeah, I mean the original mass in the West, I've heard, I mean, I'm not a specialist in
this, but I've heard that it was either entirely in Greek originally, or at least included
this.
significant amount of Greek, certainly to this day, if you go to even a Latin mass, there
is a significant chunk that is in Greek, where they're singing Kiddia Lasson and Kristä Lasson.
These are not Latin phrases.
Right.
And so very into the second century you've got really its only Christian circles and only
within the liturgy and the church is kind of thing that Greek is being used.
This means unless you-
in Christian circles and growing up in Christian circles and around Christian circles, you are less and less likely to be fluent in Greek.
And so there comes to be a general social pressure while we need to translate this into Latin so that people can understand it.
over the course of those couple of centuries, though,
by the time you get to the late fourth century,
beginning of the fifth century.
Because now Latin is being used in the churches, Latin is being used by Christian authors.
Now in the West there's no real compelling reason for anyone who's not a scholar or doing
trade with the East or something similar to learn Greek.
And so everything then becomes Latin.
And when you get toward the end of that, the big events that we tend to...
think of in terms of Latin translation. So St. Jerome's Volga, right, his translation of the Latin
Bible of the Bible into Latin or the Bishop of Rome at the time of the late fourth century
doing having a Latin mass per se, right. Those are not the first translations. Translations had
that started long before that.
But those are...
standardizations. St. Jerome was brought in not to translate the Bible into Latin
into which it had never been translated before. There were Latin translations of the Psalms already.
There were Latin translations of specific books of the Bible, but they were different in different
places and had been done by different people. And they were being used in churches, but
but they were very angry.
quality. And so, say, Jerome's brought into standardize the Latin Bible, not to be the
first translator. And there was a whole uprising. The first RSV KJV fight happened not in the
1950s in the United States. But in North Africa, at the beginning of the fifth century, when
they got St. Jerome's Psalm translations and people literally rioted.
It's over the churches because the psalm translations they were used to got replaced by these new
woods and that was like the end of the world.
See, people don't change, folks.
Individual people change over the course of their life, but people as a whole, people as
a group.
We don't change that much.
So there's the standardization of the Latin.
And then as we mentioned, the fact...
that now Latin is being used everywhere in Christian circles.
And the fact that Christianity is now the religion of the Roman Empire by the time
we get into the end of the fourth beginning of the fifth century means that,
as we said, there's no compelling reason for the average person living in Christian
North Africa or Western Europe to learn Greek.
And so people don't.
Why is that a problem?
Well, because as we said, the way translation works, especially in this case, we tend to think
somewhat naively that there is a word in one language that equals a word in another language.
Right? Like, what is the Greek word for tree? What is the Greek word for dog? Right?
Yeah.
And that seems...
to make sense to us as long as we're talking about nouns like that. Sure.
You could go in your yard and I could point into tree and I could say, you know, I call
that a tree. My friend next to me could say a lot of bull, you know, and we could go,
oh, okay. Yeah. Those are the two words for that thing. But when you get to concepts,
What do you get even diverbs?
Right, denoting actions, especially abstract actions.
and abstract ideas, homo-usios, right? When you get to those kinds of concepts and words, right?
It's not like you could just point at something, right? And so what you're doing now is you're finding a label in the new language, as we said, to apply to the concept that has a certain Greek label.
and Greek label.
And you don't, you know, you don't do that at random.
Right. You don't say, okay, our word for homo-usios is going to be canis, which means dog.
Right. Like that, right. You're trying to find something in Latin that's as close as you can get to that concept.
Right. And there's a sort of reliance in that first generation.
There's this rely.
on the fact that that first generation is familiar with the concept. Right? They're familiar
with the concept. They're just learning the Latin word for it. Okay. Problem is, right?
You go a couple of centuries and the only access the people a couple of centuries later
have to the concept is
is the Latin word that was chosen.
Yeah, so early on the word is picked
and the concept is still understood,
but they picked a word that fitted as best as possible,
but kept the understanding.
And then later on after the understanding gets lost,
all that's left is the meaning of that particular word.
I mean, we have the same problem right now,
Orthodox Christians in the United States
using English words from the Bible.
That means something quite different outside of the Orthodox context, like the word salvation,
for instance.
What does it mean to be saved?
That means something very different if you were a Baptist versus if you're an Orthodox
Christian, and yet they're both using the same word.
Right.
Or even what we mean by grace is different if you're a Roman Catholic or a Protestant or
a Orthodox Jew.
Yeah.
Yeah, exactly.
So you have this slippage.
And so especially when you get to the point where there's nobody who knows Greek, you don't
of easy access to somebody.
Greek. Because if you have someone who knows Greek, they could be like, oh no, no, no, no, no, no,
right. That Latin word was used for this Greek word, right? So think about how
regardless of your Christian religious background, you have probably heard sermons or read articles
or read books where someone will take an English word in the Bible. They'll take an English translation
a Bible verse that they'll say.
Well, this English word is being used to translate this Greek word, which actually means more like XYZ.
Right.
Because the English word doesn't quite match.
And that's fine if you have someone around who can read the original language,
it's sort of keep correcting that.
Right. So that the concept is handed down generationally, and the word doesn't mislead people.
The other factor you have, not old.
is no word a perfect translation for the concept, but words also change meaning over time.
Yeah, I mean a great example for instance would be, you know, John 1-1, right, where, and our he and
a logos gets translated in English as in the beginning was the word. As long as you have some
understanding of what logo means and you use the word word, you're probably fine. But if you say,
Well, it says in the beginning was the word and we know that this
meaning Jesus, that means that Jesus is a word. He's just something that's said. Right?
That would be way, that would be the kind of distortion that we're talking about where
all you have is the word, the later word, you know, the translated word and you've lost the
original sense from the original. Or people who use the term word of God to refer to the Bible.
Yes, that's a really obvious good example. Yeah, right.
We read that phrase, is that referring to the Bible?
use that terminology all the time now.
Well, a lot of times if you're reading
like St. John's Gospel,
that's actually referring to the person of Jesus Christ,
not to the Bible, right?
Yeah.
So yeah, so words change their usage over time.
And with Latin, we're talking about like 15, 1600 years.
Yeah.
Right.
And so words don't mean the same thing,
1500 years later that they met originally.
Right. There's drift. And so you get this slippage. And so you go from
Christians who are generally aware of the concepts and just expressing them in Latin
to centuries and centuries and centuries and centuries later,
Christians reading a Latin word in a text and reading a bunch of meaning back into it.
from the current usage.
of those words, right? In the same way that sometimes people do with the English Bible.
I don't know if I've told this story on this show before, but one of the worst sermons
I've ever heard was a guy who was, I mean, he was doing his best. I'm not meaning to
really pick on him. It's just this went horribly wrong.
He was going one verse at a time, right?
Yeah.
This is not Jayverna and McGee.
He was a positive.
A total of preaching.
Right.
But he's going with one verse at a time, which normally is fine, as long as you keep
track of context, which is what's going to be the problem.
He gets the parable of the Good Samaritan.
He reads the first verse, a certain man was going down to Jericho.
and we need to be certain in our faith.
Oh man.
Right.
It's he that's what he'd done.
Now, if you know the Greek, you know that what's translated there, the King James has a certain
man is just some guy.
Right.
Some guy was this one.
There was once this guy.
Right.
But he was preaching from his English Bible that necessarily look up the Greek to see that.
The word certain right has this other me
right? Then you're right back into it.
And it's great. I mean, you mentioned also, you know,
that words, of course, change over time.
Like another classic is in the original version of the King James,
the word conversation is used in a number of places I think in,
in a number of places in the New Testament.
St. Paul talks about your conversation.
And now we use that word to mean like what you and I are having right now.
They were talking to each other.
But
in the 17th century, your conversation was the way you lived your life.
You know, so if you think it's only about how you talked to other people,
then you're going to come up with a very different interpretation.
Right. Well, and I've, I have recently, a certain Protestant
apologist who I won't name who is not a stupid man, but he made a similar
mistake is reading the conclusions.
the enathomas of the seventh acubedical counsel, where an enathematized is anyone who communicates
with iconoclasts.
Oh, no, no, no, no.
And then he said, you're not even allowed to talk to them.
Oh, see?
Wow.
No, it means you can't have communion with them.
Right.
You don't share, you don't share community with them.
You don't celebrate the Eucharist with them, right?
That's what it, right?
Yeah.
That's what I usually bet.
Communication now means...
right? Yeah. Share discourse, right? So these are all examples, right? And so
happens a lot of this happens with these Latin translations later on, right?
They are perfectly good, well done, incredibly well done, right? At the time
they're done, right? But history then takes its course, and you get this slippage,
Right, you get these shifts.
But even at the time that some of these translations are done, right?
So that's an issue of time and usage, right?
But even at the time they're first done, there are some little shifts that happen, right?
So in Greek Orthodox listeners have probably heard this.
Other folks maybe not so much.
but the distinction that is weighted orthodox.
theology between worship and veneration. The Greek words are Latreia for worship, which
means service. And proskineo, which proskineo means to literally to bend the knee, like
to bow down. And that's what we use for veneration.
In Latin, the word for veneration is veneration.
Venera.
Venera to you.
Yeah.
And the word for worship is adoramus.
Yeah, from which we get modern English adore.
We adore.
Right.
Right. Adoration.
Yeah.
Here's the thing though.
Adoramus.
The Latin word, etymologically,
is from aura
to pray and add to or towards. So it means to pray to.
Yeah, etymologically, yes.
Right. Yeah. And the great thing just to give us some confusion in the
reformation. Yeah. Like just to muddy the waters, even in English,
when you use the word worship. Now most people when they hear that word
worship, they understand it to mean something to the effect of
stuff you should
do or you do towards God or or a God. But the irony is that actually in most of the history
of that word in English, it is referred to what we would call veneration. It comes from
the word worth, sort of worth ship, sort of to recognize the worthiness of another. And
we still have a couple of echoes of that usage in modern English. So for instance, judges
in the UK maybe called your worship and by that
No one means that they're offering religious sacrifices to them.
And then of course also very famously, the Anglican wedding service includes the phrase,
with my body, I've the worship, when the husband and wife talking to each other.
And they do not, again, mean that they are treating one another as gods.
They mean that they're showing respect and honor.
But of course, now when we use that word worship,
it typically mean it, mean by something you do towards God alone.
question, of course, really is what is the action that you are doing that you're using
those words to describe?
Right.
What is the concept that we're labeling with those words?
Yeah.
Right.
And people fall into this thing a lot.
A lot of the questions we get, right?
And we'd be nice to call them questions about objections or something of worse.
They'll say it will make some distinction like that, right?
something
we'll say, well, I here, I found the word Latreia, or I found the word worship in this hymn,
you know, before that cross I bowed down in worship, aha, caught idolaters.
Right.
We are not, right.
We are not, uh,
a scribing to a word. I don't know if this will hurt some people. I'm a certain political
situation in
the United States, but words don't actually mean things.
Yeah, people mean things.
People mean things by the words they use.
Yeah.
So, uh, you could fumble over words.
You could use words incorrectly, right?
But you're still trying to convey something.
The meaning is in what you're trying to convey.
Not in the words you may mistakenly use, if you use them in correctly.
And so when we're making that distinction, we're
a label on the two halves of that distinction, but it doesn't matter what label you put, we can
make up words like they made up the word atonement, right? We can just make up bleep and blorp,
right? Bleep is what you offer to God alone. Blorp is to give something the honor it's due.
Yeah. Okay. We're just using the words to differentiate the concepts.
Yeah. Okay. The words themselves are not super important.
And if you think
they are, you can have a real problem with what we tell you our next example.
Because our next example comes from the terminology used for the doctrine of the holy trinity.
Yeah, try to try to follow this closely if you can. This will be a little bit difficult,
probably. Okay, so there is a Latin word, substancia, from which we get modern English
substance right and there is a
Greek word, epostasis. Right, and both of these words in both their parts
etymologically mean the same thing. So, Sub in Latin under, Ipo and Greek under,
stanzia, standing, stasis, standing. So, literally standing under, understanding underneath,
Yes.
So these words are the whole calcs of each other.
that they literally the parts all translate one for one.
Right.
So you would think that with these two terms
or applied theologically and Latin and Greek respectively,
that you would translate epostasis as substancia.
Right.
Wom, wom, wom.
Yeah, no, they're not.
Classical Greek.
Not the language classical Greek, but the classic framing of the doctor to the Trinity
in Greek is that God is one in Oceia and then there are three epostasis.
Yeah.
Whereas the classical framing in Latin is there is one substancia and three persona.
Yeah, so even though epostasis and substancia literally, it'll logically mean exactly the
same thing.
They're being used in very different ways in Greek and Latin.
Essentially opposite ways.
Substanceia is used in Latin for God's oneness and in Greek,
people of Stasis is used for his threeness to try and simplify it for people.
Okay.
So if you come from the words mean things squad, we got a real problem.
Yeah, no, it's not the words mean things it's that it's
words are used to mean things. Right. Right. People. Right. Because here we have a very counterintuitive
example of those labels being applied. Right. That doesn't make sense under that understanding. Right.
But the conceptual idea of gods of the unity of God. Right. The unity of the Godhead of the divine
nature, right?
and the concept of the three persons of the Godhead, right?
That concept is in both of those,
but it is framed in different terminology.
The terminology does not match up in any kind of direct or strict way
between the Greek labels and the Latin labels.
Even though conceptually they're being used to talk about the same reality.
Yeah?
Finally, this is the complicated one.
The Greek word, the Greek word,
Enteria, versus the Latin Actus.
So, in Aristotle, you find a distinction he makes between
and dynamism and energy.
Okay.
which music is translated into English as
something like power and energy or energies
Well now yes, yeah
In the past it was typically translated through Latin right. Oh, yeah, right that in and of itself calls an issue
And for Aristotle these are ontological terms. These are metaphysical terms
These are two ways of being present
Okay, you could be present, right?
And so his classical example is an architect, right?
Even when an architect is not designing a building,
he is still an architect, right?
And so when he is not actually designing a building,
Here's an...
architect essentially in
dynamis, he has the ability, the power, the potential, right, to design a building.
And that makes him an architect.
Right.
There are also times when he is designing a building, like he is in the action of
designing a building, right.
He is doing it.
Yeah.
Right, and that is when he is an architect in
NRAIA
It is he himself designing a building
So he is an architect not because he is able to design a building he is an architect because he is designing a building
Okay, that's the distinction he makes now that second category
NRAIA
that
term is used in the New Testament. That term is used in the Father's St. Basil makes great
use of it, for example. And then becomes ultimately part of the essence and energy's distinction
in Orthodox theology, as that gets elaborated fully. But, uh, in our yeah, right, when you
He's talking about God.
He's God Himself present in action.
Right.
It is God-God-ing.
And then you can distinguish the divine energies.
So God creating.
We do not encounter God in his essence
with all of these capabilities to do these things.
We encounter him in action doing those things.
Right, we're done.
encounter God in His essence, which you could talk about,
its relationship to love itself, we encounter God loving us
and the rest of His creation.
Right?
That's very hard to distinguish and Latin.
There's not a good Latin word for any.
And so...
So those terms, denomies, and area get translated to Latin as potensia and octos.
Potensia for denomies, just kind of a power and ability, right?
And octos, which means something more like an effect.
These are not ontological or metaphysical categories per se.
Latin. That's why I say they're not a great translation. If you're going for just one
to one correlation of the words, if you understand the concept, then it's a fine label to
slap on it. Right? But if you don't understand the concept, you're not going to get the concept
from the Latin word. And so because this is more like power and effect, right? A person
possesses powers.
possesses potentials that can then be actualized.
You can bring about an effect.
You can use that power to bring about an effect.
The architect has the ability to design a building.
This is no longer about his identity as an architect or his presence as architect anymore.
This person has this ability and then he could go and actualize that ability by actually
a building. But Octus does not refer to his presence in the process of designing the building
within the action of designing the building. It refers to the building he designs, or at least
the design of the building that he produces. There's a produced effect. And we could do a whole
episode just on this. Maybe we will someday. Who knows? Who knows?
Because the way this affects, if you start thinking about it, the way this is going to affect
Latin Theology's view of ordination.
Of presubishops receiving powers, carisms, and powers that they can then use to
do things to bring about effects.
Very different than the orthodox, participatory understanding, based on the idea of energies.
But we're not going to do a whole episode on that.
We're just using this as another example here that we can go into further.
But this is a particularly potent example pun intended, because it is based on this
distinction, once we lose sight of the original concepts on which these Latin labels were put,
you get the death
of God is actispurious, God is pure act. Yeah. Right. That he he is not in the midst of any activity.
Because that would apply change or it would apply parts, it would apply separation within God.
Yeah, you can see how like this idea of
potential and act, which is in the Latin words. If you have this idea that God is pure act
that in other words that everything that he can do he is doing. He has done.
Yeah, has done. It's a pretty straight line from there to hard line deterministic Calvinism.
right and from that you get the ITF
that God is, all of God's attributes are identical with his essence. This is one of the things that's
entailed by actous purists. That, yeah, which causes lots of problems. But again, that's a whole
episode unto itself. So the early Latin fathers, states of the church, holy Christian men,
Understand.
Understood.
the concepts apart from the Latin words. They understood the concepts that they were using the
Latin words to express and communicate. Right. But Latin writers later on centuries later were
dependent on just the words themselves. Yeah, like an extreme verse of the concepts. An extreme
version of this is the KJV only Protestants. You know, who have literally sacri-lized
the King James Bible.
as being sort of handed down from God as it is exactly.
In other words, they don't care what the words are translating
because they have this English Bible and that's all there is.
I'm not saying that the later Latin writers are doing that.
I'm just saying it's an KJD onlyism is a extreme version of that.
Yeah, not later Latin writers.
See, I'm going to be mean.
See, we've already... I'm going to get accused of this anyway.
So I'm not going to hold back.
Trent basically does that.
Right.
Because sort of the mark of a true KJV only person, right?
Because you know, there's people who just prefer the King James, right?
For various reasons.
I could empathize with them, right?
Like, there are a lot of things going for it as a translation, the English of it, the
poetry of it.
Right.
But the real KJV onlyist is the guy who thinks he can correct the Greek from the English.
Yes, I love those people.
Okay, okay, okay. Well, literally surrounding and post Trent, Rome said you could correct
the Greek that was then circulating like a racist Greek from the Latin. Amazing.
Trent made the Latin vulgar as it stood at Trent, the biblical text.
By the way, all the type of indicators.
I just have to break in just for fun.
Because there's someone in the YouTube chat right now who doesn't believe that we're actually live because I'm talking to them in the YouTube chat at the same time. So serve builder.
Yes, we're live.
I'm talking to you both through the chat and on the show.
Builders is a Dutchman.
I don't know it might be a relationship to here.
I don't know. Let us know, serve builder.
But, yes, no, Father Andrew just doesn't pay attention while I talk.
It has nothing to do with this big pre-recorded.
True, my attention does drift sometimes.
You do go on.
Yeah, I don't blame you.
I'm just saying.
My attention trips while I'm talking sometimes.
At least my attention to thought is I'm like, I get bored with what I'm saying.
It's thinking about something else.
I mean, it's great.
And you know, in French, you bore yourself.
Is it a moment we?
Yeah.
Uh...
That's why I have to keep drinking caffeine.
So, the first sort of major Latin theological writer, at least who gets credit, right, is
Trotullion.
And we all know he flakes out, goes and becomes a mountainist.
Yeah.
So there's nothing to do with the mountains.
as everything to do with Montana's.
I mean, his name means mountain, but yeah, the crazed heretics.
Right. Yeah. But I mean, like, so like much later in church history, the 19th century,
you have within Roman Catholicism the ultra-montoness.
Ultra-montonism, I know.
Yes.
We're not, I mean, you're a super-monitor.
No connection between these.
We should tell. I mean, I'm just going to put this as a request.
We should do an episode on mountainism.
and
it's it
Yeah, the original one because it's before the fourth century, which you say you don't
care about anything after the whole century.
Oh, yeah.
I mean, you have to care about it.
No, Montana's and his two female prophetesses who he traveled everywhere and stayed with.
I know nothing's sus.
Anyway, let's go to Tolian.
Yeah, started well and then someone could cut in on him and he flaked out, but his main
to
Latin linguistic fame is he's the first one that we know of to use the term Trinitas.
The word that's used in Greek of course is trios, which means technically trio.
But who we're really talking about though and we talk about who frames
And we've at least mentioned this in passing on the show before who frames not Roger
rabbit, but Latin theology, uh, in terms of its terminology, pun intended, and, uh, the
general scope of it is, of course, St. Augustine. Yep. He's, he's the guy. Um, and, uh, as we
always say, despite, uh, accusations, otherwise, hitherto in Yon, St. Augustine is a saint.
Yes. Objectively, he is a saint of the Orthodox church. He's commemorated out June 15th.
Yes, you can find them in actual cynic sardiya.
Yes.
There's a canonical icon of them here in my studio.
He's called a church father by ecumenical councils.
Yes.
But really, this is... here's the core thing guys.
If you want to know if someone is a saint in the Orthodox church,
are they in the cynics area, are they on the calendar?
If they are, they are.
If they're not there.
Are they actually being celebrated?
Purely objective.
there is no subjectivity to this, right?
And objectively, say to Gus,
it is a saint, he's named a church father
by the Fifth Hek Humanicle Council, right?
So no shade is being thrown at him.
He is the one who ends up creating
most of the later Latin theological terminology.
And by that, I don't mean necessarily,
he's the first one to use that word.
a particular word in a theological context, Christian theological context, but that it's
his usage. It's the way he applies those labels to concepts that gets picked up by later
writers. Part of that is for historical reasons. As we were talking about, if you think about,
We were talking about that frame where people stopped.
learning Greek and just no Latin and St. Augustine is living during that time. So St. Augustine himself
does not know Greek. Right? His Greek is shoddy at best. He was to Greek as I am to singing.
But he was in the church that was formed by those concepts.
In.
So he understood the faith, right?
But because of his lack of Greek knowledge,
he's expressing it entirely in Latin, right?
He's taking cues from Latin translations
that he's reading, but he's also having to frame
a lot of things himself.
And so in St. Augusta, despite his lack of Greek knowledge,
you still find that as we were saying about
the early Latin fathers,
he is by those Latin words, implying Greek terms.
I don't know if you can see it.
you read him that way if you read St. Augustine, as not implying later Latin meanings with his
Latin words or later Latin usages, but implying the Greek Christian concepts, you can understand
why the church fathers of the East who read him during his life and thereafter did not think
he was teaching something radically different than them.
they read them in context of
of that period's theology in the church at large.
Yes, it's not because they were also teaching medieval
Roman Catholicism or Calvinism.
It's because they understood St. Augustine
to be teaching the same thing they were teaching in Greek
just in line.
That was their reading of him.
And it's that reading of him
that has a recognized as a saint.
But later generations reading St. Augustine, right, and St. Augustine writes this voluminous amount of work in Latin.
Okay.
And most of the rest of the church fathers are in Greek still in the late fourth and early fifth centuries.
Yep.
You got a few people like St. John Cash and some of the later people, but you do not have a lot of Latin mothers.
And so for subsequent generations who only know Latin, St. Augustine becomes their whole,
he is the fathers essentially, for a lot of future generations.
Right? The fathers is, you know, 80 or 90% St. Augustine, and then some other writings.
And that, of course, causes some of the slippage we are talking about.
Not in the sense that St. Augustine caused theology to go wrong.
but that the slippage and language
and in context, historical context
causes people to read St. Augustine differently over time.
That said, if you wanna hold St. Augustine guilty of something,
that would be integrating platonic metaphysics
into Christianity.
He is the one who does that.
Some of the things like divine simplicity and stuff
that we're-
just talking about do come in with St. Augustine and then become ubiquitous in the West. But in
addition to just the word slippage, the word usage changing, all those things we've already talked about,
people fail to read St. Augustine as a whole. They fail to read him systematically and they fail to
to read him contextually. What do you mean they fail to read him contextually? Well,
He retracted a lot of stuff that he wrote.
Right.
Daetrin Atate in its entirety toward the end of his life,
St. Augustine refused to have copies made,
because he said there was nothing in it worth reading.
Basically put it out of print, so to speak.
Yes. Nonetheless, Daetrin Atate became the basis for
all-trenetary theology of the West going forward.
Okay.
Um.
He also published his retractions.
Right. This is, this is one of the, one of many reasons to admire St. Augustine as a saint. Right.
That takes a lot of humility after you've written a whole bunch at the end of your life to look back on it.
And essentially public a book, publish a book listing all the things you think you got wrong now in hindsight.
Hmm.
Right. That, that's something. Right.
Uh, uh, me...
I mean, why is it that, of course, there's other things
that he did retractions on as well, yeah?
Yeah.
So most, certainly not all, but the lion's share of his
retractions actually come from his anti-polagean writings,
sorry, Calvinus.
The stuff of his that they love most is the stuff
where he basically says it is retractions.
He kind of went to an opposite extreme in arguing against Pelagianism.
Oh, so a lot of the stuff that like hard predestinerians super love is exactly stuff where he's like,
yeah, let's scratch that.
Yes. Whereas like that, that quote we gave a few episodes ago, he made it the city of God about
astrology, say that God does not control all wills. That statement was made three years before he died.
Yeah.
So unless you think late St. Augustine is his dying utterances that everything else was retracted,
that's pretty close to the end of his life.
Yes, so the question is why is it that these retractions are not wider and more widely known or
just sort of get ignored? Well, first of all, they're boring reading. That's true. They'll be
I feel like reading Irohda, you know, for...
Yeah.
you're reading a rata yeah and there's by the way just there's a relationship
at the point he did not retract a single word of his treatise on the freedom of
the will but yeah so they're not they're not great reading in order to really
understand them you have to have read all of the rest of St. Augustine yeah which
pretty much no one has.
Honestly, there's like, and I-
I'm not one of these people.
I am not read all of St. Augustine, not even close.
I read more than the average bear, but like,
not close to all of it.
There's maybe five, like St. Augustine scholars
in the world who have read all of St. Augustine.
Like literally.
Yeah.
I mean, so we haven't read at all.
You're not gonna know what he's talking about
in the retractions a chunk of the time
because he's referring to works you haven't read.
You're not going to know the context, right? So the reflection is really hard to read effectively
Unless you have this really thorough going knowledge of his works already
Going into it
But also
But also when it's up happening in the West frankly by the time you get to the Reformation it's
People pitting parts of St. Augustine against other parts of St. Augustine
So the reformers, both the Lutherans and the Calvinists, right, are latching onto stuff
from the anti-Polation writings, so teereological stuff out of St. Augustine, and quoting
him to back their positions.
And Rome is latching onto his sacramental theology, his ecclesiology, you know, the fact that
He's a bishop and a monk.
You know.
got to fix and arguing in the other direction. Right. And so trying to have this sort of
comprehensive understanding of the man himself, the saint himself, and what he understood,
and how he understood things at the end of his life was not nearly as useful as weaponizing
quotations in an ongoing argument.
I think he's been done wrong.
And he serves because of that,
he serves as kind of a test case.
Right? The fact that you could have people
with sort of radically different views on things,
both grabbing stuff and quoting it.
Right? This shows you how that original context
of the late fourth and early fifth century
and those Latin fathers is lost a thousand years later
by the time you get to the time of the Reformation.
Yeah.
I don't think I've done this on this show.
I've only referenced it.
So I will do this.
I'll do this relatively quickly.
Here's a test case on St. Augustine.
Right?
St. Augustine, what St. Augustine himself, the saint,
believed and taught about original sin,
is neither the later Roman Catholic view,
nor the later Protestant view.
Yeah.
because both of those hinge on different interpretations of essentially the concept of guilt.
In fact, you will generally get both of those groups saying that St. Augustine taught
original guilt. In the case of Luther and Calvin, they're going to argue that
that guilt is essentially forensic, penal, criminal case guilt. Right? Everyone is born guilty
of Adam's crime, the penalty for which is eternity and hell. The penalty for which is spiritual
death. Okay. In that kind of structure, by the way, your own personal sin is kind of completely
irrelevant. Right? It's like getting convicted for multiple death sentences. Like you can
It only got to go to hell once.
Right? So, whereas, whereas the understanding of guilt in Roman Catholicism is much more
nuanced, we're going to get into that a little bit in the in the second half, right? But
it is more in the concept, in the context of a debt or a liability, which is actually
closer to the word that St. Augustine actually uses in Latin. In Latin, he doesn't use the
the word the-
you would normally associate with guilt, the Latin word, culpa, right?
From which we get the English word culpable, right?
Guilty, responsible, right?
That's not the word he uses.
And that is a word that St. Augustine uses.
So for example, it is owed to the Paschal candle, the only hymn or poem we have that he wrote.
He uses the phrase famously, phaelic's culpa, right?
Happy Fault!
Right. Oh happy guilt. Oh happy sin. Talking about Adam's fallen to sin and calling it happy because it brought about so great
a salvation. So he's capable of using that concept, Colpa. He has that. It is tool chest. That's not what he uses to describe what people
inherited from Adam. What he uses to describe what people inherited from Adam is reatus and reatus in Latin is
can
mean a lack, a liability, an extreme a debt, right? So you can see the later the medieval
Roman usage of it is closer to St. Augustine than the Protestant Reformation usage of the
term, what they read back into it. But, but, this is why it's a good test case here.
It's not identical to the concept that St. Augustine was trying to express.
And the way you can see that is, again, if you read some more St. Augustine, because we
have to say, okay, if we're saying that some element, something about the sin of Adam,
because he doesn't just say every human being is born with Adam sin.
says they're both the rea to us of Adam's set.
But something about Adam's sin, he's saying is inherited by every person who is born on
this earth.
We have to look if we want some clues into what St. Augustine means, we have to look at
how St. Augustine views sin.
St. Augustine does not view sin as a crime punishable by eternity and hell.
So now he talks about send that is
doesn't work with his platonic metaphysics.
Okay?
He doesn't even really talk about it
in the sense of a literal debt
that has to be repaid.
He talks about sin as a privation,
a metaphysical privation and lack.
Yeah.
And so what you actually find is that
Sinegas and talks about the effects of the fall in two.
closely related ways that show you what he means, what he believes, human beings inherit.
One of those is the grace that gets referred to later in Latin theology as the super adenum bonus,
that Adam is created and Adam as created is partaking in, participating in God's grace, from the
moment of his creation.
When he is expelled from paradise, he is deprived of that grace.
And he has to receive that grace anew.
So part of what St. Augustine is saying is that every human who is born is born without
that participation in God's grace, and they have to come to participate in God's grace anew,
namely through baptism. That's why you have to baptize a baby.
Second piece.
So this
second piece is has to do with a Greek distinction we already talked about
dynamis and in our yeah because if you understand Aristotle's view of virtue and you can
go read the nicotine ethics if you want to understand that better but
virtue, right?
is an acquired property, right?
It is an excellence, but it is an excellence
found through exercising a power, a dynamism
that you have in an excellent way, right?
IE, you have a, if you were talking about humans and ethics,
you as a human have the dynamism,
of power.
to right love, to run, to jump, to think, right? If you do that,
excellently, if you do that well and you do it well habitually, right? That is,
that is virtue, right? But, but for Aristotle, the fact that those things have to be
habituated
those virtues have to be acquired means that for every
dynamis possessed by a nature, right?
So it's used human still, by human nature, every dynamis,
also entails an odd dynamis.
A not potentiality.
Right.
Right, a an impotency, right?
Yeah, not the possibility that it will not be exercised at all
or will not be exercised excellence.
So the other piece for St. Augustine, St. Augustine is trying to put this concept across as
this privation.
What is A, when you attach it to something in Greek, it is the alpha-privative, right?
St. is a privation for St. Augustine, right?
So now, right, Adam for St. Augustine is created excellence.
right? It's created virtuous in all of his human powers. Right? Now humans are born with
this adhenomace, this impotency, this right possibility that those will not be actualized. This
pretend city to decay, to air, to fail weakness, right? Those are the two core things. If you
really look at the way Saida Gustin talks about this.
Right? Both of those things are the same things taught by the Greek fathers.
That nowadays it's labeled as quote unquote ancestral sin over against quote unquote
original sin. But frankly, if we're just talking about Satan,
gusting himself, he's not teaching anything different than the,
than the Greek fathers on this. But he comes to be read differently.
Yeah. Later in history. And then radically differently by the time you get to the
16th century reformers.
Well, beyond what he says.
So we mentioned there's this period right after St. Augustine these immediately subsequent generations where St. Augustine is the fathers
Yeah, and really kind of a bottleneck
Right, and so this period of time is often referred to as the platonic period in Latin theology
It's you know starts with a figure like beefyus, right who
writes his own date for Natatae, which is basically
notes on
state Augustine state Trinitate.
They're not identical, but I mean he contributes things,
but I mean it's he's building off of,
he's standing on state Augustine's shoulders, right?
He's better known as constellation of philosophy.
Right, which is overtly platonic, right?
And then goes to Anselm.
I know everybody thinks satisfaction theory and atonement
when they think of Anselm now because of Kourdeus Homo.
But he also wrote the prosologian and the monologian
Bye.
He wrote literal dialogues, right, like Plato's style dialogues.
Remember, he also came up with the ontological argument for the existence of God, right?
So Edsel was a figure who's deep in platonic metaphysics and in most of his works.
And so he's, you know, sort of the last big fear.
There are other figures, of course, after him that we're going to get to in the second
but that's going to be sort of outside this potas.
period. And just as a fun fact, Father Andrew didn't know this. One of his interlocutors
in one of his dialogues is named Bozo. I did not know that. Which is where the clown gets his name.
I hope that's true. Because, well yeah, no, I mean, that's the reason we both, because,
imagine the interlocutors in Plato's dialogues, right, they're all kind of dumb, right?
Right?
Yeah.
So, same kind of thing.
Right.
And then finally, during this period, we've mentioned this on the show before, but you can
see already, as you get into the seventh and eighth centuries in Latin theology, there
start to be debates, and the debates have a particular character.
So what example we've used on the show before that we'll use again now is the debate between
retrameness and rad-burdists on the Eucharist.
where they were arguing about whether in the Eucharist it is Christ's crucified body
and blood or his resurrected and glorified body and blood.
And the reason this is a good example is it shows us the questions that are being asked
and theology.
in this period. The debate is about what the Eucharist is. And those debates are going
to continue right right into the Reformation, right? What the Eucharist is. Yeah.
Rather than what you see in the East in treatises on the Eucharist, which talk about what
that the ugrist does.
And part of that difference is that the concept of
the Eucharist as a mystery, the concept of apophaticism,
the idea of the transcendent, the idea that if there is a way
that these things quote unquote work,
it is concealed from all seekers, right?
It is miraculous, it is beyond human understanding.
The West becomes far more confident in human reason.
and there's.
a shift in how they understand reason. It's subtle at first. It takes a long time for
this to finish happening. But even as late as Thomas Aquinas, you find, I would tell
us Aquinas talks about the news, essentially, using the word, in-electum. But you very soon
after that, you start getting some slippage in how in-electum is used. Meaning it is
Is it really pointing at the same concept as the Greek word, new sinny more?
Yeah.
So there is this, and there comes to be this very confident view.
We'll leave it here for this first half.
We'll see how this develops in this second half.
It's very confident view about the ability of human reason to understand the details, the mechanisms of how God and salvation work.
All right, well, we've just spent 80 minutes on basically late antiquity.
We're not going to quite get depart from it yet in the second half, but we're going to head into the middle ages.
So we're going to take a little break.
Much less boring. So we'll move quicker.
That's true. We're going to take a little break and we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of spirits.
Give them a call at 855-2008
372346. That's 855 AF radio.
Ancient near eastern texts, such as the Ball Cycle, who tray the pagan god Ball as a rebel,
a hero of a revolution, worshipped and glorified for his long string of victories. In the Ball
A biography of the devil.
Father Steven D-
The young shows that the Hebrew scriptures consciously turn the ball story on its head, depicting
him as a failed and defeated rebel who, nonetheless, tries to steal the glory that belongs to Almighty
God.
From these scriptures, the figure of the devil emerged within Jewish and Christian tradition.
Father D. Young works through the old and new testament passages that refer to various
ball stories and a survey's ball worship through followers beliefs religious
practices and liturgical life.
In these pages, we will see that the figures of the ball and the devil, the prince of demons,
are one and the same.
To find this book and others like it, you can go to store.enchantfaith.com.
Again, that is store.enchantfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen De Young.
If you have a question, call now.
8552372346. That's 855AF radio.
Hey, welcome back everybody. We're, uh, we just spent 80 minutes talking about
late antique developments in Latin theology. Um, we're not going to quite leave that
yet. You're really focused on that 80 minute thing. Like are you worried about your bedtime
already? Is that what's absolutely?
You're going to ride home on your ball cycle.
I'm just wondering if it might be, I don't think it's a record for a single half for us yet.
I don't know actually.
Oh no.
But first halves go along a lot.
It's true.
But we do actually have some calls.
Are they happy?
I don't know.
We'll find out.
But yeah, we have.
Have we got that mean yet?
So we have.
I know.
We have Eddie calling from Texas.
And Eddie is wondering about some of the words and stuff, the Greek and Latin words that
we talked about on the first half.
So Eddie, welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Thank you for having me.
So father and the young, you got me confused.
I thought I knew what I was doing and now you shift the foundations.
I always thought, well, first off, I thought it was Latvia and now I found out it's Latrea,
so I've been staying at Rago all the time.
Wait wait, you said Latvia? Latvia?
Latria. Latria? No, it's really Latria. Don't don't don't follow Father Steven's Greek pronunciation.
It's it's vaguely a rasmian. Yeah, I thought it was Latria and then he said Latria. So then I
felt like less of a man than I already feel like just normally. Just listen to your local Greeks
and how to pronounce Greek buddy. All vowels that diphtongs are ease. That's right. Go with it.
Yeah, so I thought it was
Latria and Dulia and then you threw in proskenesis. So how did those three words fit together?
It was my question.
Well, go ahead, Father.
Latria and Dulia are kind of synonyms.
Yeah.
I mean, like literally speaking, Latria is service and Dulia is service like from a slave.
is to serve, yeah.
Yeah. So they're kind of the same thing. And then proskini sees is, you know, veneration
bowing literally. Yeah. So, so the orthodox veneration is strictly, they're okay, because I,
and then I had to explain to me wrong then because I was told. It's about the concepts, not the words.
right but I was I was I was told Latria is the worst to be
to God. Doolia is what we give to the saints. Am I totally wrong on that or?
Well, so what I'm trying to say is that it's the concepts that are important. Don't get hung
up on the work. Yeah, the actual actions. We could call it leap and blorp. Yeah, we put
bread and wine on an altar to God. We bow, we name churches after, we make icons of saints.
we see
their praises. But we do not give them sacrifices of bread and wine. You see the difference?
Because if you put all the emphasis on the words, like it takes just a few minutes searching
to find some hymn or something where one of those Greek words is used differently.
Yeah, like for instance in the the feast on January 13th of the veneration of the chains of
the apostle Peter, there's a lot of translations of those texts where you can say you can see where
as we worship your chains, O Peter.
And it does not mean we're offering sacrifices to those chains.
It just means we're kissing them, we're,
you know, venerating them, we're showing them respect
and honor.
So the key thing is really the actions.
And sometimes the words can slip around.
Like proskinesis can sometimes get used to refer to worship.
You know, but the question is, what is the action being done?
Gotcha.
and kill it.
is this possible? Can I
slide him one extra little
short question? Sure.
Sure. I've talked to both
you independently on different
podcasts. And now that I'd
have you together, I would
like to know what would it
think for you to watch escape
from New York Father. Damick.
You need to see that movie.
Well, first you'd have to
pronounce my last name correctly.
I did. I for now that
incorrect. I'm afraid so. So
that means you've lost any
I hit my thumb with the...
hammer. I know when my dad was in the Navy, he used to say that he was never sure whether
someone was cussing at him or calling his name because they would all misproductive.
No, I said, damn it. See, that's still wrong, buddy. That's not correct. It's dammit. It's
dammit like night and day. Mick. Yes, as opposed to an Irishman at night. Right. I'm a
the loser life you got got me.
I'm gonna get...
Man.
I sometimes wished that my great-grandfather had left the name where it was, which was Dumaika,
but-
Yeah, that would be way easier to pronounce.
Yeah.
He apparently thought that Americans couldn't say that or whatever, I don't know, so
he got Damick.
It still has all the consonants are intact.
He just did a number on the vowels.
Oh, well.
Well, I still think you need to see Escape from New York and then we can revisit the issue
down the road.
Thank you so much for taking my question.
I genuinely appreciate you too.
Thanks for calling, Eddie.
All right.
I think you two is overrated.
I prefer our ham.
Wow.
That is the spiciest take of the evening.
There you go.
So we have how much you have to be to call yourself the edge and dress like a pilgrim all the time.
That's true.
It's true.
So we have Rachel calling for more not creed California, who says that she has an um actually to deliver.
the translation of a
specific Greek word mentioned in a previous episode. So, so Rachel, are you ready to deliver
your um- actually? Welcome to Laura Spirits podcast. Oh boy, can you hear me? We hear you.
Oh, okay. Yeah. Well, I guess it's an um- actually. I was more just curious to hear where the
source of in the in Genesis 3 in the garden that this Satan is described as a serpent and I
I heard Father Steven say that the Greek word
is a track on dragon and I can't find anything for that. I always every
version of the Septuagint or the the Greek Old Testament that I can find says
Ophiis like serpent which just means serpent. So that was
those the thought there and then I had a broader question about translation.
Okay. What did you say? Did you in fact say that, Father Stephen? And if so,
It's a textual variant.
I think he has like next all of his action figures on the shelf, which is real. By the way,
there's photos of this. He has some. Oh, you don't know the half, brother. Right. I know.
You're going to come down here and visit anyway. I'm ready. I'm ready. Yeah. I mean, I'm already for Kajin food during Lent.
But yeah, I don't you have some like text somewhere, some massive volume that shows you every textual
variation in like the Greek scripture.
Well, yeah, it's getting published. Yeah, basically, yeah.
Yeah, yeah, I have, I have, I have books that have photos of all the New Testament,
papyri, I have books that yeah.
See, see, see,
do you remember, do you remember happening,
happened to remember offhand which manuscript tradition or whatever that was new?
I do know. Okay. Yeah.
No, but if I if I didn't say it was
textual variant I should have. Okay. If I said that's just the word that's there in the Greek,
then that would be an incorrect statement. So I would accept it, um, actually on that.
Okay. Yeah. That is what I said. But I don't remember what I said. So, but you can, you know, who
knows? You can go spend the points that you got for them. I'm actually Rachel at any, at any good books
near near you. Oh, I will. Okay. So what is your broader question? Yeah, I'll try to keep
Basically, I've heard you guys talk about that in some ways America is kind of like the
new Babylon, the new Roman Empire in a lot of ways we are.
One way I would say that we're maybe not is that we speak English and at least in a lot
of those, you know, like Greek and Latin and stuff, there are abundance of Orthodox texts
in those languages.
And so far, at least that I'm aware of, there's not really a whole lot of English.
to that point but I'm really just like for us as native English speakers is it incumbent if we
have a pension for languages or anything like that of on us to learn these you know orthodox languages
I've heard you say that a lot of orthodox texts are still not available in English so
So should we just wait for someone to translate these?
Should we take it on their word?
Is it a good idea?
idea for us to go ahead and try to understand it better that way.
And the languages that we should be learning,
you know,
I don't want to be spicy, but, you know, I don't really understand other than the scriptures like Hebrew,
you know, really like it hasn't been an Orthodox language in like 2000 years.
So wouldn't it make a lot more sense to learn Greek,
what Islamic language is, Georgian, Romanian, languages that, you know, Orthodoxy.
actually have use. So yeah, that would be.
Oh, oh, can I start with this one?
I will. I mean, number one, like you started off saying that you did not think that comparing
the United States to Babylon is a good comparison because there's not that many Orthodox texts
in English. There's way more in English than there were in ancient Babylonian or, you know,
languages. There's speaking around that area. And I mean, Christianity has been in
English.
in one form or another for 1,300 years?
Something like that.
Yes.
I mean, honestly, I liked to mention this
to some of my friends and seminary.
Christianity arrived in English before it did in Slavonic.
So, yeah, absolutely.
Absolutely.
The earliest English texts we have,
Actually, the earliest English texts we have are all Christian-
and they date from at least the 8th century probably earlier, which is long before the conversion of the
ruse, centuries earlier. So yeah, I mean, you know, like St. Cadman's hymn is one of the earliest
English tech, is possibly the earliest English poetry. There's another text called the Dream of the
the root, which might be a little earlier, but they're both 8th century at the latest, maybe
the seventh century. So I mean, the question of orthodox languages, you know, I don't know
what you do that because like there's a huge amount of variety in terms of languages
that have had orthodox theology in them for centuries. You got everything from you know
like Arabic and Georgian to Romanian to Slavonic to Greek, you know, on and on. And yeah!
Of course, the presence of the church in those places
can have a transformative effect on the language,
but at the same time,
like the form of Arabic that is used
in the divine liturgy in the Middle East
is essentially the same form of Arabic
that is used in the Quran.
So what do you do with that?
Like is Arabic an Orthodox language?
I mean, it says in the Bible that Arabic
was one of the languages that was heard at Pentecost.
You know, with the apostles there.
Right.
So I think the question is, I mean, if one is going to be a scholar, you know, you should
learn the language of whatever it is that you're studying.
Absolutely.
But the fact that like, let's say the only language you speak into English, that does not
mean that you are cut off from understanding orthodox Christianity.
Now, you should probably hesitate to...
You know, say it say things say authority authoritative sounding things about certain matters, right?
If you don't know like any Greek, for instance,
which is probably the most useful language to learn in terms of orthodox theology.
But but you're not cut off from and you're certainly not cut off from being a saint.
You know, like you know, we have a newly canonized saint saint, olgo Velazka. How much Greek do you think she knew?
you know I'm not even sure
much Slavonic she would have known, even though they do know that they use Slavonic in some
of the churches in Alaska, but she probably was worshiping in her own native language.
I don't know. I'm just speculating. I have to talk in my head. But she's a saint. So,
yeah, I mean, it's good. It's absolutely great. Awesome to learn these other languages.
But I don't think that I think the idea that there's a sort of sacralization,
like at what point do you consider the language to be an Orthodox language? Like, when does
Does that happen?
How long does it have to be in that language and used for what?
You know, I don't, I don't think there's a good answer to that. And, and even also there was early on, there was something
will not super early on. There was something called the trilingual heresy, which is where some were, were actually preaching against the new
invented Slavonic language because they were saying, well, you know, Christianity really should only be expressed in Greek, Latin, or Hebrew because those were the languages
that we're on.
the titulus that hung above Christ's head on the cross, which is nonsense. It's just nonsense.
Finally a hair is the egg can get behind.
So, yeah, you know, language becomes holy by using it for holy purposes.
That's the kind of what I mean.
Yeah. Yeah. So English...
Like, languages that orthodox people use, they have a history of using,
and that have engaged.
with orthodox theology in those languages,
to understand it from like an English speaker's perspective.
Yeah, I think if you attend the church a lot
and you read the scriptures and you listen to the preaching
of your priests and the catechists and your parish,
you're going to have a good understanding of what it is you need to know.
You are. If you want to go beyond that,
Then yeah, maybe you should do some language study.
And that's great. I mean, we need more people doing that. So that's allowing you to give the minority report. Go for a father.
Well, first of all, Arabic did not exist in the first century. A.D. is a language.
Not as it exists now. That's for sure. No, it didn't exist at all.
There was a what proto-Semitic, whatever? No, it was dialect. They were speaking a dialect of air-MAIC.
Yeah, yeah, it's doubtful whether Arabic even existed with
the current was written. That's like a big debate about. Yeah, sure. But also, it defends
of Hebrew and Aramaic. You're not going to be able to understand the Bible in Greek,
unless you know some Hebrew and or Aramaic. I agree. Because it's full of Hebrew and
Aramaic grammar, even though they're writing in in Greek, you're not going to be able to
learned Georgian without knowing some air mag.
Syria is a dialect of Arabic is essentially spin off.
The Georgian thing I'm not too sure about because I do know some Georgian I have no idea about Arabic.
Well, there are segments of the church in Georgia that use Arabic as a liturgical language.
Oh, I see. Okay.
That's what I was getting at.
And Georgia had early on extensive contacts.
with the Syriac slash Aramaic speaking world.
I mean, the earliest church in Georgia
was actually under the Church of Antioch.
So, and Semitic languages, once you learn one,
picking up others is relatively easy.
So you can learn Ugric death curses?
Yeah, I mean, that one is an outlier admittedly, right?
Unless you're like super-indulctestimate studies,
fair enough skipping Ugric.
but there is a lot of Syriac.
Christian Syriac literature that's untranslated. There's even a fair amount of Arabic literature.
The majority of the church father was still untranslated.
Yeah. So those like, dip your toes in some big languages is not unhelpful. But just in
general, every American listening needs to hear this. One of the best things you can do
in life in terms of enriching your life.
and broadening your understanding of things is learn another language.
Absolutely.
Even if it's just to read it.
You know, I know there's a whole, this is Merca talk Merkin, right?
And because English is sort of spread everywhere, you don't have to learn another language.
But people, because of that, deprive themselves of a lot of good things that come with learning
another language. If you're going to learn another language, why not? Right?
one of these orthodox languages and then, you know, once you've learned it, why not help with the translations?
Yep. I hope that helps Rachel.
Yeah, thanks guys. You're the best. God bless.
Alrighty, thank you. Okay, we're going to take John who's calling from Toronto.
John has a question about pagan philosophy. John, welcome to the deep in the heart of Pnecastan.
Yes, yes. Thank you, Father. Can you hear me okay?
We can hear you okay. All right,
fellas,
bless. Thank you so much for your show.
I'm, you know, my wife and I are huge fans.
We really love it.
It's replaced primetime television for us.
So I think that's a huge compliment to how great the show is
because we watch it every single day.
So thank you again.
My question is about.
You use that as a tagline that we're better than the CBC.
But well, uh, okay, don't get,
don't get me started on the CBC.
That might not be your favor.
But you were truly excellent show.
So my question is about pagan philosophy.
I'm trying to connect a few things that you mentioned on the show about the gods of
the nations and about the pagan gods.
So if I've been following an understanding correctly, the pagan gods are demons, right?
And the pagans who wrote pagan literature and pagan philosophy were also deeply religious.
People like Plato.
word can they be they
followed the religion of their time, right? So the basic thrust that it is, I guess from my perspective,
like I came to orthodoxy late in life, so I would say different backwards. I studied the philosophy
first and the religion second, and I regret that I spent so much time studying philosophy and
didn't start with scripture and go the other direction. So now that I'm trying to kind of fix this in
my life, why study pagan philosophy if you have not mastered the Bible, mastered the fathers
And I'm interested to because I know from studying philosophy that there were many orthodox people,
obviously, who studied it as well, right?
Like Basil wrote a letter about it.
You stay in the US, wrote a huge commentary on the Iliad and the Odyssey in the Middle Ages.
So there must be some reason to do it.
I'm just trying to understand what it is and that's my gap.
Okay.
Yeah, I mean, as you know, a lot of the church fathers studied that stuff very closely and
understood it.
I mean I think the
best ways through, like what St. Justin Martyr says, for instance, essentially he says,
anything that's good or true belongs to us. Right? So this idea that, for instance, that,
you know, if Plato says something that's good, that's true, it doesn't have kudis by virtue
of his being a demon worshipping pagan. It's still good and true. Right? So, you know,
himself said that he got a lot
of benefit out of the various
philosophical schools.
that he belonged to, which are essentially religious groups, okay? So everything that's
good is good, and belongs to us Christians, as he would say. So that's the short response
I would give. I don't know. Father, do you have anything more or less or other?
Well, I think, so for example, Aristotle, it is organ, right, the categories, the
posterior anelitic, uninterpretation.
Is basically teaching you how to think
and how to use language with precision.
That's why St. John of Damascus, the first part of his
Fount of Wisdom, is his commentary on Aristotle's
organite. Right.
defining theological terms. Here's what we mean by
here's what we mean by this, here's what we mean by that.
Here's how you put together arguments,
here's how these things are constructed.
I think that by itself, you've heard me
how probably often say how much various scholars
need to take a logic 101 course.
And that's a good logic 101 course.
So I think that there are elements of that, right?
that are sort of critically important.
Because if you don't understand those,
you won't fully understand how the fathers
are interpreting the scriptures
and how they're making arguments
and how they're putting these things together
and how they're getting from point A to point B
when they lay things out.
So that alone.
I think justifies a certain amount of Greek philosophical education.
I think in the abstract, just, you know, the presacratic, even Plato, are actually far
That's helpful.
But a lot of the categories in Aristotle are so important to understanding Orthodox theology,
because they are the under-girding of just how you think and how you argue and how you structure things.
I think they're kind of necessary not to understand the Bible, but to understand the fathers
and how the fathers understand the Bible, which we hold as the correct way to understand
the Bible.
Yeah. Yeah. Does that help John? That does help. It's like I'm going to add one quick clarifying
question. So if we kind of follow pagan philosophy through to modern times, are there writers
that are dangerous to read like Nietzsche is often read by many people as a heuristic,
you know, as a source of ideas to apply to other things? But some of Nietzsche's ideas
are pretty disturbing and very empty Christian. Is there any value in reading someone like
Oh man, don't get him started on Nietzsche.
Don't you read it every lunch, father?
Lens about to start.
Yeah.
Yeah, I've read Nietzsche every
lent for decades now.
But that doesn't mean I recommend everybody.
Go and read Nietzsche because most
most people are reading Nietzsche.
Read him really badly.
Treat Nietzsche and understand what
that they're just trying to do even.
That it's definitely not all good what he's trying to do, but to even understand what he's trying to do and be able to assess the good and the bad.
You have to be pretty well versed in Hagle, which is a gymnastic feat all do itself.
You get some Dusty F ski, you need some Chopin hour.
I don't recommend reading Chopin hour to anyone.
You know, all of life is suffering, but especially reading Shope now.
So yeah, so I mean, it's definitely not, it's definitely not for everybody.
And Nietzsche in particular, there's not like a bunch of other Nietzsche's, right?
Like, I could say, you know, if, if, Heygill, you really can't understand without a good
teacher because he writes up to Slee.
That can be helpful in terms of understanding,
I mean, we're going to talk later on in this episode,
the third half, understanding certain social and societal movements and things.
Right? There are ways in which reading some of that modern philosophical stuff,
you could say, oh, that's what's going on with that movement over there,
or that school of thought.
Right? So it can be helpful in that kind of way.
Nietzsche really doesn't work that way.
And that most of the stuff that's quote unquote inspired by Nietzsche is inspired by some weird bad reading of Nietzsche.
So actually reading a good understanding of doesn't help you understand that.
Yeah. Yeah.
All right. Well, thank you very much for calling, John.
All right. We're going to take one more call. We've got Nicholas.
We have to wait for Jordan Peterson to get out of the hospital to talk about Nietzsche with him, I guess.
Oh, boy.
We could take one more call. I've got Nicholas calling from the state.
to my east, the Garden State itself, New Jersey.
Nicholas, welcome, Lord of Spirits podcast.
Thank you, Father, for having me on.
Yes, you're welcome.
Yes, what's the called?
I have a question.
Since you're talking about the word, concept, talismacy
and we live in the English-speaking world,
a lot of the Bibles we have in English are,
At least in my perspective, I have a very heavily Protestant.
and bent. And so, do you guys have any recommendations for Bible translations that try to mitigate that perspective, if you will, because like I know you brought up before words like Latria and the Pruskinesis and then in a year.
So I've only come across maybe two Orthodox translations
that make attempts to try to bring those concepts forth.
So I'm open to hearing.
what you guys have to say about that.
This is your forte father.
Give your spiel on Bible translations.
Yeah, so,
if you aren't gonna be learning biblical languages,
or at least not anytime soon,
I always recommend to people of the NET Bible
as long as you get the full notes edition.
The translation is not that great,
but if you get the full notes edition,
like most of the pages know.
There's like a little box of translation and then like the whole rest of the page is two columns of notes.
And the notes are not like study Bible notes interpreting it.
They're translators notes about the original language that's behind the English translation.
So it'll give you all the information about right here's the Hebrew words, here's how the Greek has it, here's how the Syriac has it, here's how the Latin has it.
That's it. Right.
in those notes. So you can kind of get back behind the translation a little bit without
learning other languages that way. And since the NET Bible, again, you got to get the full notes
edition because you want the notes more than the translation. It's in the public domain so you can
get it cheap. Like you can get a hardcover copy for like 25 bucks online. You can get like a
whether bound one for like 50 or say the net Bible yeah I mean it's it's a you can
and netbible.org and read all the notes.
It's all. Yeah, you can just download it all. Yeah.
I like how it's usually for free. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah, if you want a printed copy because you're like me, then you know,
you can get it cheap because it's public domain.
Anybody who wants to can print one.
And then, you know, um,
the Easter Orthodox Bible is fine. It's, you know, I mean,
I don't think it makes a radical difference over most other English.
New Testaments, but it's fine. They're going to be coming out with a book that's going
to bind together the Lexum English Septuagint, which is a good English translation of the Greek,
even though the Canon listed it as a little wonky. And the Easter Orthodox Bible New Testament,
So I'll probably get one of those when it comes out. That'll be a nice thing just for your day to day do the readings, you know, kind of kind of use.
But yeah, that's.
Yeah. All right. I hope that that's not bad. I've been for that.
No.
I mean, we do publish your book, the whole Council of God, which has basically everything you said and lots more at the end of it.
So that's true. That is true.
Yeah, yeah, so all right Nicholas thank you very
much for calling. All right, well, we're going to move on. Where are we?
Middle ages. You are in a Mayas, Pennsylvania, I believe. Oh, there was
see now you know, you know, we're getting late. We're getting there was some
there was some guy in the chat who kept asking me like, what what town are you
related located in? What exactly where are you? I was like, it seems little.
Oh, did I just doxie? Stop asking you do you do doxie me, man? Actually,
everyone knows exactly where I live. Yeah, this is gonna be like, what about Bob?
Is this gonna be uh...
I have to tell you though, I'm kind of excited about moving because the area in the in the
Raleigh area that we're looking at moving in moving to.
There is an unincorporated like town or village or whatever it might be that is actually quite
famous.
And I'm really hoping that I can get my new studio located there so that I can tell everyone
that I will be coming to them from Lizard Lake, North Carolina because it is a real place
that I could be living in or near in the near future.
Everybody pray.
that my studio can be located in Lysard Lake, North Carolina because that would be awesome.
So great. There you go. Yes. I still remember there's a sign in Cross-Lanes, West Virginia
that says they're the largest unincorporated area in the United States.
I said, wow, here's the biggest group of people who can't get their act together.
They're proud of it.
No trash pickup for us.
Thank you very much.
So yeah, so now we come to the middle half of the show.
Indeed.
And the middle ages.
See, that's a segue again.
See how it goes?
Nice, nice.
Yeah.
And so as we get into really the high medieval period,
Land theology completes this turn toward soteriology.
The doctrine of God at that point is kind of fully enshrined in Latin theology in platonic terms.
When you read the authors of the period, there's not a ton of difference on the way they express the doctrine of God.
And that's coming from St. Augustine through some of the intermediaries we talked about.
but that's pretty much firm down and so there's a move of focus to...
anthropology and so taryology. We already mentioned that a little what we were talking about.
How Ed Selm wrote not only the prosologian and monologian but
Gurdas Homo, right? Why the godman on
Atonement.
So even though
this shift sort of fully happens at this point it really started earlier. It's
picking up a thread that began much earlier.
in the history of Latin theology and that began with the whole issue with
Blagianism. So, Plaegius was a British monk. That great early English-speaking
Christianity that Father Andrew was just going out about gave us Blagius. Do you know, do you know, do you know what Jerome said about him?
I'm sure he said a lot of things, but which one in particular?
Yeah.
Well, I mean, of all the church fathers, St. Jerome is the man in terms of hilarious insults.
Yes.
And what he said about religious is that he was, he came up with his heresy because he
was too full, and this is the, how it usually gets translated in English, too full of
Scottish porridge, which I have decided means that this is a man who came up with a heresy
where you literally did not need the help of God.
to be saved because you've been eating haggis.
Yes.
It's got to be the fact that you've been able to successfully consume and live on
haggis would give you a kind of overconfidence and human ability.
That's exactly right.
To eat that much of it and not die.
Do they even have the neaps and tatties in those days?
I don't know.
But I do recommend the neap and tatties next time you have haggis.
So, uh, yeah, so he comes to become sort of an actinetic preacher.
And the log line of his preaching is that he is preaching moral theology.
He's tried to bring about moral revival, as it were, among Christians in the early fifth century.
Now that Christianity has become the religion of the empire, now that it has become fashionable
in advance.
contagious to become a Christian. There are a lot of folks in churches who are not fully committed to living Christian lives.
Right? So he is going to come and improve the morals of the church.
Uh, Trotullion was all about that too.
So just a note, a historical note.
This retends to repeat itself.
When you see people who the focus of their preaching and their message is primarily on morals.
Hmm, a lot of times down the road there ends up being an issue.
Yeah, so just something I've seen yeah half a century on this earth
But so ladies does this and in arguing for sort of
rhetorically in his rhetoric
toward
Increasing people sense of frankly guilt of culpability, right for sin and trying to drive them
to repentance and urge them on to living a moral life.
Several people, including most notably St. Augustine,
think he is going a bit too far
in terms of how he talks about human capability
to work out your own salvation
without the assistance of God.
is
So, St. Augustine tries to handle this through the proper channels.
He finds out that Plagius is within the territory of the Bishop of Jerusalem.
So he has the Holy Synod of Jerusalem, pull him in and examine him for heresy.
Here's the problem.
There's only been two ecumenical councils.
And so the bishops...
only ask him about the doctrine of the Trinity, which wasn't the issue.
So they clear him.
They say he's not an heir.
Take, he's not an heir.
And say to God, it goes, no, that wasn't the point.
And so what comes to be known as pallagianism, right?
And this is a broader thing.
get these modern folks.
sometimes who want to say, you know, the story is wasn't a story and the plagues was
an Applai engine and blah blah blah blah blah blah.
Right.
Fine, you know, whatever.
But you have to understand that when the councils, especially after the first two, where
the councils can dab something, certainly plagues just had some followers of disciples,
like Celestius, who went further than him.
Um...
on these things. But they had learned from arianism that when you condemn very
specifically one guy's view, you're going to have a whole bunch of other guys show
up with similar views who are going to say, well, no, I don't technically have
that precise view. So I'm okay. Even though your view is very similar, that's the
semi-arian's, right, who had to be dealt with at the second
the Second Medical Council and the following councils.
When there's a problem, they say, okay, what are all the variations we can think of of this
bad idea?
We're going to condemn all of those.
And what are the consequences of these bad ideas?
What are the presuppositions that would lead you to these bad ideas?
We're going to condemn those too.
That doesn't necessarily mean that any given figure who held to a form of that heresy, held
to all of that.
Right?
In fact, it's all-
unlikely that anyone person held all that because sometimes the things they can damn don't fit together. They're like variations
Where you'd only hold to one of them right logically
But the idea is these are ideas that are dangerous for human salvation
These are ideas that if you follow through on them will endanger your salvation and so the councils are
warning you away from them. They're putting up a fence between you and that whole area
to keep you away from...
from it. So the question of what elements of this play the historical play
G is held isn't totally relevant to the condemnation. Right. But broadly speaking,
for a quick definition, since father Andrew needs to get to sleep sometimes soon.
But wait, what?
Exactly.
Is that plagiarism is the view that divine...
grace, the action of God is not necessary for salvation. He did not deny the existence
of grace, he did not deny the forgiveness of sins, right, plagians do not deny that these
things are there, they just deny that they're necessary, right. And in some variations,
this gets down to like at the second council of orange, this gets out to the detail of
the fact that
that God acts first. Right. God acts first. God acts God saves to put it in very short form. God saves you. Right. And you cooperate with God in your salvation. Yeah.
Whereas in various forms of polygionism, the activity is...
is shifted away from God and toward the individual person.
So the way polygeneism ends up getting condemned at the Third
Eccumenical Council, because you're like, wait, I thought that was about
Nistoryus. It was. By the time you get to the Council of Ephesus,
St. Augustine has departed this life. St. Augustine passed away a year before the
Council.
So
through a long confluence of events, St. John Cacheon was in and around Rome at the time.
That point was Archdeacon Leo. That point in church history,
the Archdeacon of the city of Rome was sort of the on-dex circle for the next bishop of Rome.
So the next the next Pope was generally made the archsticative Rome.
preceding it and this Archdeicolio is the man who became St. Leo, the great as the Bishop
of Rome. But he was friends with St. John Cache and had St. John Cache and write a treatise
against the story to represent Rome's position on the story and his deposition to take to
the council of Ephesus.
And in that treatise.
St. John Cacheon connected Pelagianism with Nestorianism. He argued, and so St. John Cacheon
had come from the east, as most of the eastern fathers do, his understanding of
Soteriology flowed directly from his Christology. So he says, in Christ, as Christ works
our salvation in Christ his
human and divine energies are in perfect cooperation.
Perfect cooperation.
And therefore in our salvation,
the grace of God, the divine energies,
and human energy are in cooperation,
or in perfect cooperation.
And so by separating human activity from God's grace,
by holding those apart,
Belages and the plagians are de facto
separating the divine and human natures in Christ
And therefore they are essentially historians and that's how he gets roped in that's how
Plagias gets roped into the third ecumenical council for
condemnation
Let me add, as is my wand, that
semi-plagianism is not a thing you guys.
semi-plagianism is man bear pig.
It is it is something the Calvinists invented in the 16th and 17th centuries to
call their enemies as a slur.
It does not correspond to any historical belief, especially not St.
John Cashin who gets labeled as that by the reformers.
Yeah, in a twist of irony since he's the one who got plagias condemned.
So, but within, within the context of these discussions, terms get used, some Latin terms
again, that become very important in later developments of Latin theology.
of those is grace, gratia.
And one of those is merit.
And so within the context of these discussions surrounding polygionism, merit is the term
that's used for human activity, human intergea, who are in Latin at this point, human actus,
right?
Even though as we've said, that's a flawed translation.
and grace is being used for divine action, divine inner air.
right to find actus in the Latin translation. And so for example at the Second Council of Orange,
the major question decided by the council is, can you merit first grace? Now when you hear that
as a modern person, especially if you're like here in the US or in the rest of the Anglophone world
that's been deeply colored by
uh...
You hear, oh, can you earn grace?
It's probably what you think that means.
Yeah.
Right?
Can you merit first grace?
So first grace, in this case, is baptism.
Right?
Because baptism, when you baptize infants, especially, right?
That's the first sort of partaking of God's grace that you receive,
as we were talking about with St. Augustine.
Kid.
you merit that? That doesn't mean earn. That means can human activity bring you to that?
Meaning in terms of your salvation, do humans act first or does God act first? That's the question
there. They're deciding. Now, the decision, of course, is that no God acts first. And then humans
response. So there's nothing anywhere there about earning anything and
and pledges to not.
say anything about earning anything. It's the idea of earning salvation through some means.
Is nowhere actually in any of these discussions. Right. Um,
a plagias just thought that the the effects of Adam's expulsion for paradise were very minimal
so that a person could by their own determination and their own habituation
form the virtues.
right of love, right of faith, of hope within themselves, right?
With minimal, right, assistance from God.
God stepped in when, oh, you messed up, you sinned, okay, forgiveness, right?
But then you get back on track and it's your own efforts.
That's Malaysianism.
That's still not earning your salvation, guys.
Right?
That's still not...
That idea wasn't there.
Yeah.
PID.
that especially keeping the Torah somehow would earn you your salvation. It just doesn't exist at this point in history, in Latin theology even.
Great.
So, that's sort of the first, the beginning of so,
materialological discussions within Latin theology.
But as we said, once we get into the Middle Ages,
sort of Latin theology is a whole sort of search
to turn in that direction.
One of them.
most important figures if you're going to talk about the sort of next phase of Latin theology
is Peter Lombard. Lombard was not like his last name. No, he was a Lombard. He was a Lombard.
Yeah. Peter the Lombard basically. And he's living in the middle of the 12th century.
And he writes a work called the sentences.
This is not the first work called the sentences, but it's a very important one.
The earlier works called the sentences are essentially Florelegia,
meeting collections of quotations from Christian church fathers, from the Scriptures,
from councils, right, all pulled together.
His is an important watermark because he sort of does that
in a more systemic
and comprehensive way in his sentences.
And so he pulls all of that together into one place.
Probably the closest equivalent,
because he also, it's also set up as a basic work of theology,
like the first part of St. John of Damascus is found
of wisdom that we mentioned for this commentary on air.
the Aristotle's organ on the categories in particular.
Also, it's even a little bit like some of the early stages of the filicalia,
although less, it's got the characteristics of Latin theology by now.
Right. So whereas the filicalia is very much aimed toward prayer in an apophatic way,
the senses are aimed more toward.
theological reasoning, right? And theological reasoning is not bad, like I said, it's
like John and Damascus, right? It's a similar kind of thing there. It's not bad, just different.
So that becomes such a formative work that throughout then the next few centuries, the
at universities that the newly founded university.
universities in Europe, people are going there and studying the sentences and it becomes
very common for new budding theological writers to write commentaries on the sentences
on Lombard sentences.
But probably the biggest theological idea that comes out of Lombard sentences in terms
of the flow of Latin theology is he is the first one to make the distinction between the
efficiency and the efficiency of
Christ's work. And in this case, we're we're we're post
Kourdeus Homo. And so in the West, more and more, Christ's
saving work has not completely been narrowed, but just been
shall we say focused on the cross? Rather than the incarnation
in his life as a whole, particularly the cross and then
the resurrection. But the cross and
becomes sort of the focal point.
point of the understanding of Christ's work. And so for him, the importance of this distinction
is, first of all, we have to say, right, that Christ's saving work, right? And now if
we're in this Latin theology mode, we're focusing on the cross, he would not have to do something
more in order for one more person to find salvation.
Right.
So there's a certain number of people who are going to find salvation.
It's not going to be everybody.
There's a certain number.
But for one more than that to find salvation, he wouldn't need to do anything.
Okay.
So what Christ has done is sufficient to save anyone and everyone.
At the same time, right, universalism has been rejected as heresy.
And so it is not going to be efficient.
Is that going to be a...
Effective, it is not going to effectively save everyone.
Right, it's going to only effectively save a subset of people.
Now, you may have noticed if you know something about Calvinism, Calvin has a very different
way around this, right?
So technically, under Calvinism, in the view of a limited atonement, Christ would have to
do something different to save one more person.
because he only died for the sins of the elect, for have a subset of people.
And therefore he collapses
sufficiency and efficiency essentially.
But Lombard makes this distinction,
and it becomes critically important.
So then the so-treatological discussion
becomes in the West,
or sorry, slipped in theology.
Oh, dear you, sir.
I know.
It's a vigilant over here. You think I'm
taken an app, but I'm not.
How do you get?
How do you get then?
Right?
From Christ's work, which is
sufficient to save you, to you
actually being effectively saved,
right, to your salvation being
accomplished for yourself.
Right?
And so the term that gets repurposed,
Right.
and you're you see a shift in meaning here. The term that gets repurposed is merit.
Okay. And it's only a slight repurposing because as we talked about, right, merit before was being used
to talk about human action. It's being used here to talk about Christ's action and what Christ
Accomplishes as man, right, Crudez Homo, right?
Accomplishes as man, Accomplish.
in the incarnation, accomplishes in the atonement, right, accomplishes in work, our salvation.
So we're talking about Christ's merit. And then that merit is seen as a sort of mediatory element.
Christ's work, what Christ does, his suffering in particular throughout his life and especially
at the cross that produces merit.
And that merit then is applied to people for their salvation, to humans for their salvation.
So we're sort of mediating between the universal and the limited, right, between what, you
know, Calvinist, B.B. Wurfield will call redemption accomplished and applied, right?
But there's a couple side effects
of seeing it this way. So merit has to be quantifiable. Right. What do I mean by that? Well,
it has to be quantifiable because it's not applied to everybody. Right. It has to be a
thing. It can't be this infinite thing because if it's a truly infinite thing, then it would
just overflow to everyone. Right. So that's to be quantifiable. That's to be
be containable.
Right.
S.
be finite in some sense, to be able to be moved to some people and not others. It has
to be created in some sense. Right? It's not eternal. It's produced by what Christ does
on the cross. It doesn't sort of always exist, right? In the merits of Christ.
that this understanding of merit and its relationship to grace, to God's action, right,
then is going to lead to a shift in the view of what sin is, right?
So here's part of where we see the idea of sin as debt, more firmly taking shape, right?
In a sort of more literal sense of debt.
And so it's sort of de-marit, right?
You're merit, de-marit, merit, credit, and debit, right?
Notice over it.
still not gerinical guilt.
Yeah.
Yep.
It's still not like criminal charges.
And so the understanding comes to be in the medieval period in Latin theology, Pat.
There are a series of deposits, right, from Christ into you.
Right.
the earth's infusions.
right at various points of this merit that forgive sins takes care of de-marit right and then
works salvation right within within a person those that happens through right the sacraments
beginning with baptism and then receiving the eucharist that happens when you do things like go on
Pilgrimage is when you do penance, when you do acts of faith.
acts of love and charity toward people, right? You receive these sort of infusions of grace. Now again,
right? A lot of Protestant later dogmatic are going to say, well, this is earning your salvation.
Technically, that is not what Latin theology is saying, right? So there is this distinction that's made
of two types of merit, con-dynemerit and congruent merit.
Uh, Codd I Marit.
is when God owes you his grace.
Now that sounds crazy right off the bat.
But the reason God would owe it to you is that he promised it to you.
Right. Right. So God has promised that baptism will bring about the forgiveness of sins.
Therefore, if you are baptized for the forgiveness of your sins,
sins, you will receive the forgiveness of your sins from God.
Right? He's only required to do that in the sense that he promised to do it and he keeps his promises.
Okay? That's condined, Mary.
Congruoant, Mary, is Mary that's given to you freely. The God didn't necessarily promise to give you,
but you did something that made it appropriate or made yourself worthy to receive it,
sort of as a gift. So this would be doing acts of kindness to others, acts of love and charity,
clarity.
for which there was no sort of explicit promise to receive grace anywhere. Then salvation
happens at the point where there's sort of a bar, there's sort of a level. And when you
have a level of merit, when you have a level of grace that you've received that reaches
Is that bar?
And is above the bar you are in a state of grade.
and if you die at that point, you go to heaven. If you are below that bar, because of mortal sin,
or just because you never got close to it, because you didn't do anything good in your miserable life,
or whatever, then you go to hell. You go to eternal hell. It is possible for someone within this
system to be in a state of grace. So be at the point where your salvation has been worked out, and you're ready to go to hell.
and you're ready to go to hell.
and you continue to do good deeds.
These would, this would be the Western,
the Latin theological understanding of saints, right?
Saints are people who not only entered into that state of grace,
but then through their continued lives
and receiving the grace of how these things had sort of extra.
That is put into the treasure house of the merit of the saints.
The Pope has the keys to that.
uh... to the l-gore style lock box
uh...
And he can't take your old joke.
Yeah, he could dole that out right for the, for the forgiveness of sins.
This was one of the, this is probably my favorite of Luther's 95 feces.
If the pope could do that, why doesn't he just forgive everybody's sins?
I mean, it is a very good question.
Good question.
Brother Martin.
Yes.
So now
just described it and we're doing it quickly. Right. You could read that as this very crude kind of
banking metaphor taken literally. Okay. Right. Of like withdrawals and deposits and debits and
credits and this and that, right. You get to a certain balance and okay, now you're good and
right. You can take it rather crudely. And the reality is and I know there'll be some
rowing kelp, I suppose we'll get mad at me. But the reality is part of what brought about the
the Protestant Reformation, honestly.
that your average peasant in Western Europe understood it in that crude way. Yeah. And there
were people like Tetzl taking advantage of them in that crude way. Yeah. Right. And so
that was a popular understanding. Yes. That's never the way the way that, you know, bishops
and highly educated churchmen understood it. But that is the way a lot of common people
understood it. And again, to give credit to Rome first to the
counter-reformation backs away from a lot of the very literal creed versions of this.
But it's worth noting that this idea that there is this treasure house of merit.
It's still a thing.
It is absolutely still a thing.
You can go on the Vatican website which if that doesn't speak authoritatively for the
Roman Catholic Church, I don't know what does.
People say it doesn't so you know.
I know.
That's amazing to me.
Yeah.
like yo yo
Vatican one to yourself into this.
I don't know what to tell you.
Anyway, Vatican one does a verb.
There we go.
There we, I mean, I feel like it works.
Yeah, if you look at the Catechism
of the Catholic Church, 1474 and following,
you can see all that stuff and various other places to you.
So not making this up.
Not the Vatican or the Vatican.
That's what I want to know.
That a connection.
Yeah. So yeah. And so then another key element of this that we can't leave out is the distinction
between eternal and temporal guilt. Right. So guilt as liability as that here takes on two
kinds. And this is still Roman Catholic theology. I'm sorry it is. There is eternal
guilt, that's taken care of by Christ directly. Right. And then there is temporal guilt.
Temporal guilt is built off of the idea, it is sort of a formalization or a mechanization
or a making transactional of the idea of repentance as dealing with the consequences, except
to get dealing with the consequences of your sin in this world.
And so that is turned into this formal thing of temporal guilt, which the same way Christ's
suffering takes care of eternal guilt, your suffering or grace and merit from saints
who suffered, et cetera, take care of that temporal guilt.
If you have temporal guilt, if you have eternal guilt when you die, you go to hell.
If you have just temporal guilt left.
then you go to purgatory to pay off the rest of it.
Okay?
And I know, once again, Roman Catholic Church has done
a whole lot of backpedaling from the very crude way
purgatory used to be understood.
But purgatory was understood in that crude way
very recently.
Yeah, I...
You have the receipts, folks.
Yes, I mean like an example that I always think of
Back when I was in university, when I...
I was half the age they am now.
I had a Catholic girlfriend for a while and she showed me her gigantic Catholic Bible.
Were you trying to kill your parents with grief?
You've a jellical boy.
You know, I don't remember them ever objecting to her religion.
I don't know.
I don't, I don't, it's been so long, Father.
I don't even remember if we discussed it, but, um, but she had this big Catholic Bible and
in the front of it.
I mean this was like a...
real Catholic Bible, the whole, you know, Neil Obstat, all that kind of stuff was in there.
And it had just, it was huge. Yeah, it was a huge, huge, huge volume.
I mean, I love a big Bible.
And anyways, the front of it had this.
And you cannot lie. Thank you.
The front of it has charted it.
And it said, if you read the Bible for this many minutes, then you get this
amount of time out of purgatory, like it was a chart with numbers.
You know
So like, I know, I know, you know, probably your average Roman Catholic here in 2026 does not believe
that kind of quantification. Maybe I assume, but, but I mean, it, it, it, it, not that long ago,
it was definitely believed. And you can't say, oh, it was always a metaphor. You, you wouldn't have
charts like that. And like, there's some kind of, sometimes it's almost freakishly precise
and some of the language.
For many, many...
centuries it was this way. And I mean, I'm glad they've gotten away from that. Like, let's just go the whole way and
jump purgatory entirely. But hey, you know, we're making some progress here.
Yes. So yes, you have to, you know, good that you're backing away from it. You still have to own it historically.
So yeah, it's sort of this period...
of a lot of theology ends up getting summed up,
punfully intended by Thomas Aquinas.
Who interestingly, you know, he lives in the 13th century,
not very important during his life, actually.
His works and everything.
He doesn't finish his summa before he dies.
Tertius Partisquitz put together from notes
at his monastery, but he did that as a
work of basic theology, that was the intro, that was the 101 level. But he sort of becomes
the image of this period at the Council of Trent. The Council of Trent sort of enshrines
the theology of Thomas Aquinas as part of the counter-reformation,
That's sort of the basic explication of Latin theology.
during his day, he was actually more concerned with the controversies of his day
involving the recovery of Aristotle and the Latin of Aerois. I'll take Mercy
on Father Andrew and not go into all that right now. It's, it's, it's notting.
It's, I can see him nodding in my head. But so he sort of becomes emblematic of
that. But to some of the second half, I think you can see that some of the trends
we saw in the first half.
are now sort of fully coming to fruition.
Faith is it's being practiced.
Right. For sure is it's being practiced
and arguably as it's being laid out,
has become very transactional mechanical.
There's a way these things all work.
We have an ontology of the universe
that includes God and rocks, right?
In one chain of being.
We're sort of, you know,
We're not at modern sciences attempt to explain.
everything, but we're at theological science as attempt to explain everything.
Right? The idea that you could have a cohesive view of the entire cosmos and understand
it all, right? By a mix of God's revelation, Aristotle's logic, and platonic metaphysical
categories is thoroughly in the view of
of the scholastic mind.
And as you probably know, the 16th century,
stuff's gonna happen.
So we'll get to that in the third half.
On that cliffhanger, we're gonna take our second break
and we'll be right back with these completely
uncontroversial episode of The Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
The Book of Lamentations was written after the Babylonians had invaded the land, slaughtered
the populace, and brought about national extinction.
What remained for Jerusalem and Judah?
The five poems of the book represent the authentic voice of Israel and exile, a mourner
wailing over the judgment of God, desperately seeking an audience with him but finding him
hidden and inaccessible.
In prayers in the dark, Father Lawrence Farley paraphrases the Book of Lamentations and
interprets each passage.
following it with a meditation on human suffering, not to explain it, but to point
away forward into hope. In the words of the sacred text we find insurance that
we are not unique in our suffering and that the way home to the kingdom brings
pain as well as joy. Find prayers in the dark today at store.AncientFaith.com.
that's store the ancient faith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hey, welcome back everybody.
The question actually that we're getting from our producers right now is whether we are
going to outstrip the the mammoth
episode of the Aman School podcast that Michael Haldas did as a guest with Father Anthony Cook,
which I think is like four hours and 36 minutes long. I think we can beat that tonight, Father.
Oh, we can. No, if that I mean challenge accepted. Oh, no, I've said that.
Okay, it's four choices. Yeah, that's a poor choice of words there. Oh, man.
I shouldn't have revealed that was discussion was going on.
Yes.
No, no, that was a nice tidy second half.
So good job.
Good job.
And thinking that words are just, you know, names apply to things, nominalism.
If you want to test case in nominalism, here comes the Protestants with the imputation of
righteousness.
All right.
I mean, it's literally what that's about.
Yeah. Yeah. So 16th century Protestantism, wow. So the Protestant Reformation happens. And
you get a take from a lot of people, even Orthodox folks, sometimes they'll say like, oh, the
Protestants, they wanted to get rid of the bad stuff that Roman added since the split, but they
They threw out the baby with the bathwater.
I hope no one has ever actually done that by the way.
It's like, just forgot your baby was in the tub.
What a weirdly violent expression.
Yes.
But, but I actually think the opposite.
I think the actual case is quite the opposite.
I think they didn't get rid of enough.
Yeah.
Feel honestly speaking.
So.
Essentially, you know, some of our Protestant listeners who identify as Protestant, especially
those who are even jelical bent, may think all this talk of merit and stuff is, may feel
completely foreign to them. Like, yeah, we don't have any of that stuff. That's a weird
Catholic stuff. Actually, you do.
Yeah, actually we have a super relevant to this very moment call
coming from
Louisville Kentucky. So Michael, Michael, welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast. Hello, can you hear me?
We hear you. Why does everyone say that? It's a question that they have.
I sort of make sure I'm not speaking to the void.
Do you have that problem normally? I'm very beachy in of you.
you.
Coming up again.
Um, usually not, but you never know.
You never know.
But, uh,
Yeah, I just wanted to ask this, I believe, about righteousness.
You're probably gonna talk about it,
but I just wanted to get a clarification about this
because I always hear about, especially like Lutheran Theologians,
they talk about like this,
righteousness is like, you know, like we can never merit it up to it.
Like the word phrase, I've heard, you know,
the righteous can't cut mustard.
And I was trying to figure out like how it would be compared to Orthodoxy.
like what does that righteous this mean?
like how orthodoxy kind of answers that like, you know, if that makes sense to like righteousness,
like what does it mean to be righteous and you know, like how does it make sense? Because then
a Luther, you know, he kept conflicting, like, I can never be perfect or I can never be because I'll
be an idol if that makes any sense. Yeah. Yeah. Well, this is where we're going now. So yeah, how
long do you have to leave the mustard out before it can't be cut? I want to know how you,
I mean
Mustard is is not usually that viscous that you could cut it
Like what kind of mustard we deal with here? I think it has been left out
That's the problem is when you leave it out. That's when it can be that's too long. That's when you can do
Right I say this is a big mustard lover. It is probably my favorite condiment
Yeah, so we will we will
Answer this call and simultaneously move ahead. Oh right
Hey, brilliant, Mike.
Did that, so.
So righteousness would within the system, we just described within the medieval Latin system.
Righteousness would be sort of that bar we mentioned, right, that righteousness would be sort of infused
over time, right, through the sacraments, through the doing of good deeds, right,
Axe of charity, Axe of Love.
these things, and that would kind of pile up, right? And when it reached a certain point,
where you were in a state of grace, that would be you were righteous in the sight of God
at that point. You were one of the righteous. And so the shift with Luther is not to get rid
the idea of merit not to get rid of
the idea of there being a bar, not to get really any of the stuff we were just talking about.
It's just that. He makes it a one-time thing.
That the merits of Christ are transferred all at once into your account.
And all of your de-marits, all of your sin, all that wickedness, is transferred into Christ.
All at once. So boom, you are justified, you are righteous. Yes. And doesn't get taken
away from you. Right? So you can say, right then, you're saved. You can't lose that state
of grace, the Lutheran and the Calvinist system. Right? So it's just all at once. Swap.
called double imutation. Your sin is imputed to Christ. Christ.
righteousness is imputed to you, wholesale, boom, all at once.
And that, I mean, that is the core of Protestantism.
That is the core of Protestant's
materialogy.
And so
in terms of the orthodox view over against this,
stay tuned.
We're going to get to that at the very end.
Are you going to stick with us to the end, Michael?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, no, I just...
I just wanted to clarify that because I was here by the Lutheran review about like, you
know, I can every perfect.
I don't always like, I was trying to forget like, what does that righteous this mean?
Like, or the axically, like you said, I really define it.
I'm like, because especially I can see Luther's fear of like, I never can be perfect because
I come from agnostic backgrounds.
I kind of understand that fear somewhat.
I agree it's like exaggerated, but I understand it.
Yeah, yeah, right.
And so Luther was living in this fear that he was in and out of this state of grace, right?
He'd be in a state of grace and then he would sin and then he'd have to run to confession and
then he'd sin again and he'd have to run confession again. And so this view allowed him a sense of
reassurance and security that he didn't have before. Yeah. Yeah. Right. I'm saying no, it just
happens all at once. Right. Yeah. So I was just yeah, I'll definitely listen to see like the
the door of the accident.
I should like the explanation with that
because I definitely entered because it seems
I always feel like lost because I'm transferred out
but thank you, I appreciate you answering.
Yeah, thanks for calling, Michael.
You're tracking with us as we like to say.
Yes.
All right, well, let's continue rolling down the track.
So, so that Lutheran view we just described
is definitely, definitely extrinsic and transactional.
The train.
transactional should be obvious, right?
Your double imputation is obviously a transaction, right?
But it's also extrinsic.
In fact, Luther is gonna directly say that.
He's gonna say salvation is extra-nose.
It's outside of yourself, right?
It is not a change in you, okay?
This is his famous example of the snow-covered dung heap,
right?
You're justified.
still a pile of crap. But, but now pure white snow has fallen all over you all over you. So you
look like beautiful and white and pure. What God looks at you. There was a few years ago when we
were doing a lot more gardening at my house. We had a, we actually, we actually ordered rather
more manure than we intended to. Like I think that we thought we were getting cubic feet, but we
We were getting cubic yards!
So, which is literally nine times as much.
And so as a result, we were not able to use it all right away.
And so there's this big pile of dung in my backyard.
And it's snowed.
And I remember looking at that, I'm like, and there it is.
There it is. Snow covered some German street near you.
Yes.
It's true.
It was amazing.
Simplism hap
says, isn't that what the man says?
Yes, yes.
So then this is this all at once.
One time thing, boom, it's done.
Anyone who tries to come and tell you need to do anything else, or you need to stop doing
anything else, or anything at all, right?
You tell them to go pound sand.
They're trying to bind your conscience.
their preacher works righteous at you.
Right? And as we said, you know, part of the goal here for Luther was assurance. Right?
It's what he lacked. Right? It's the neurosis of constantly being afraid that he was going
to spend eternity in hell because he had it on a compressed set. Right? And so changing
this view allowed him to actually, you know, live his life.
right? But here's the problem, right? Here's the problem. It kind of it kind of
doesn't work that way. The whole assurance thing, right? Because even if you say,
right, even if you go really evangelical on it and just you just have to believe
and not even believe anything in particular, right?
That's all I have to do.
I have to do.
Do you ever believe completely sincerely?
Yeah.
Do you ever trust Christ just totally wholeheartedly?
I mean, you know, I was raised in a tradition which really emphasized this idea.
And I knew multiple people who went back and kind of, quote, unquote, got saved again
because they doubted their sincerity the first time.
Yeah, I asked, I knew a guy who was a former assembly of God preacher and I asked it if he
had the day he got saved written in the front of his Bible and he said, yeah, I got all the
dates written there.
No, man.
I mean, some of them will get baptized over and over again.
Yeah.
And connection with that.
So yeah, yeah, you know, if you really met it, right?
This is real life, right?
be honest have you ever really
done your best at anything, you're absolute best. There was no way you could have devoted
one more second. One more Iota of effort. Really? That's Iota for those who thought the
Yeah, um, let me talk about baby Yoda. I don't know if we got there anyway.
Yeah, like who puts really puts forth maximum effort, right? And so
there's still you know a massive gap for doubt
to shift through. This is also where in the Reformation particularly the Calvinist Reformation,
where you get penal substitutionary atonement, it does not exist before this
because here is where you get the shift to the idea of
fg
as forensic legal criminal guilt, right?
Where Calvin begins teaching that everyone is born
guilty of Adam Sin and the penalty that is due for it
is eternal hell.
And this is why by the way, I just had to take this a little
aside, that sometimes when orthodox are trying to do
do apologetics against Konakot West.
theology, they will say this about Roman Catholics that they believe in, you know, the
inherited guilt, legal guilt of Adam. But it is a reformation era thing. Yeah. Catholics
will straighten you out on that usually. You mean, you can't just tell another person
what they actually believe? Oh, no, you could totally as a lay person in a completely different
Church coming.
Absolutely. Tell clergy what their church teaches. Yeah. Yeah.
As long as you got quotes as long as you got a lot of quotes. Got some quotes in English.
You could do that
Yeah, but so here's where where guilt takes on that particular forensic legal flare
It's also important that
You know what we were just saying you know
I
about sincerity and all this and believing,
the reformers were not unaware of this problem.
And so, well, how do you do that?
Well, we can't have faith be the one act that you do,
right, because then it opens all those problems.
So what Solafide originally meant was not
all you have to do is believe.
What Solafide originally meant was that faith
was not conceived as an act.
Faith was something God gave you that was an empty virtue.
And what that means is, it is not a virtue you required.
It is not something you practiced.
It is not something you did.
It's just give it to you and it is purely a receptive faculty.
God gives you a faculty called faith through which you receive your salvation passively.
Okay.
That doesn't get around the problem either.
How do you know you've got it?
Yeah, especially when you're told you can't do it
Right you can't believe harder or trust harder because you know it's not an act. It's an empty virtue
Right so again attempted
Problem not solved
So
Even though obviously you have detected our critical tone, I am sure.
through the second half and the formation of the Roman Catholic side of Latin theology
and now the classical Protestant side of Latin theology.
Now we get to the point where even that all starts to fall apart.
Right? Good old Aristotle again, you have generation and then you have corruption.
And we're done with generation in Latin theology.
We're going to start with the descent of Protestantism, which ends up being fairly steep.
First we're going to talk about Protestantism in the United States.
Protestantism in the United States, the two big watershed events are the first and second
great awakenings.
The first great awakening happens before, technically, the United States is founded as the United
state.
happens within the British colonies and is Puritan and Calvinist. That is the
urlare of sort of American Protestantism. Think the mother's continent
increase. Think Jonathan Edwards not just sinners in the hands of an
angry God but also Jonathan Edwards who said the only thing people contribute
to their salvation is the
and that needs to be saved from.
Right, so that's sort of the first great awakening.
That lays this undergirding.
And so the 18th and 19th centuries
are actually sometimes referred to as the Calvinist period
in American cultural life.
That's how much that form of religion
sort of permeated American culture in those years.
But then in the 19th century, middle of the 19th century,
essentially you get to the second grade awakening, which is bluntly a disaster on all counts
unless you're part of one of the groups that comes out of it, in which case, sorry, not
sorry, still a disaster.
The second grade awakening is essentially revivalist.
in the unreviable name.
just vanished from my head.
Finny, an unreviable...
Charles Finny.
Yeah, says that there is nothing supernatural about conversion.
It takes place through the application of particular techniques.
Yeah, there's, you know, it's really, frankly, about manipulating emotions.
I mean, these are the people that put together what was called the anxious bench,
where you would have, you would put this bench
right up near where the preacher is and get some of these, you know, sinners to sit up there
so that they would be extremely close to the preaching and would feel a sense of conviction
as a result of the powerful rhetoric that's being preached and have a big emotional experience.
And that was, I mean, that's what they were trying to engender is to set up all the conditions
that they could have this big emotional experience. And that's how conversion would occur.
Right. And what we're talking about here with conversion.
right? Because we're talking about a fundamentally, again, a culture that's pure in Calvinist,
right? Christianity, right? Remember the Baptist or what are the groups of English Puritans,
right? And the early Baptist were all particular Baptist. They're all Calvinists to an extent,
Right. That's the culture, right? So we're not talking about atheists.
the United States in the second grade of awakening.
We're talking about people who,
probably we're taking to Sunday school as kids,
right, we're baptized as either kids or teenagers
and just have drifted away from the church, right,
or living riotously, right, et cetera, right.
Things have gone wrong.
And so they're just being called upon
to just sort of recommit to Christ, to recommit.
To Christianity.
and what that does
is combined with Finney's sort of very pragmatic approach and that of the other
tent revivalist is basically theology becomes completely unimportant.
Hmm, to the moon.
Yeah, you have to have that experience.
Right.
Yeah.
And we're trying to be broad, right, to cover everybody.
Right.
So it's just believe in trusted Christ.
Not anything particular about Christ.
We're not going to go into a lot of definition of who he is, what he does.
even the Trinity
falls out, right?
All these things.
And the groups that spin out of this are not only denominations that are now considered
evangelical Protestant denominations, but also the Mormons, the Jehovah's Witnesses,
the Seventh-day Adventists, right?
All come out of this kind of weird fervor, right?
And the fact that there's no emphasis on any kind of doctrine or theology allows for
that right allows for just enthusiasm. Okay. Now, well, that's going on in the United States.
Stuff's going wrong in Europe too, right? Because that's the other place where we got a lot of
Protestants. Okay, we've got the Protestant churches in northern European countries which at this
This point have become our becoming state churches.
And we've also got German ideals.
of going on. So we're we talked about these guys before we're not going to go super into detail,
but from Kant in the 18th century to Hagle in the 19th century, right? We have philosophy going on,
right? And Hagle is very much a Lutheran, very much a Protestant Lutheran. So I don't want him,
I know, but he's a Lutheran, through and through. Anyway, I'm not going to go down that rabbit trail
right now.
But so he sets forth this philosophical and frankly theological vision of a whole world
order that's infused with the Holy Spirit.
The Holy Spirit is drawing the whole world order toward perfection.
Everything is evolving toward perfection.
and humanity coming together, dogs and cats mask.
hysteria. Anyway, but all progressing, right? Everything is progressing. God is unfolding
himself and ongoing self-revelation. The world is being transformed by the forces of
modernism and enlightenment into a greater and greater place full of freedom and learning
and reason. Everything is beautiful.
Right, and so the Protestantism in
Europe becomes what we now call refer to generally as liberal Protestantism. Yeah
Not because they have
Political views related to the American quote-unquote left but liberal in the sense of enlightenment liberalism
Right liberal philosophy classical liberalism
So that happens in Europe.
And in the United States, at this point, in the 19th century,
the best and the brightest of the educated among American
Protestants go to Europe to study at European universities.
And so pastors and seminary professors are coming back
from Europe.
deep in this liberal Protestantism, bringing it to the United States.
This starts to shift the sort of classical Protestant denominations in the US in this
liberal direction.
And so you have this kind of fracturing where the second great awakening movements we were
talking about before become deeply suspicious of education because of this.
Yeah.
But also the more traditional Protestants, right,
or conservative Protestants, guys like J. Graschem-Machin
at all, right, who are at Princeton Harvard Yale, right?
And see this change happening,
want their traditional more classical Protestantism
to survive.
And so they start to, they make common cause
with
the a lot of the second grade awakening, an educated folks, at least the ones who have kept some semblance of Christian theology around.
And you get the publication of the books, the fundamentals, and this becomes even jolicalism.
Yeah.
Right.
Which has this sort of curious mix of anti-intellectualism and then several intellectuals who are seen as leaders and deferred to.
Right at the same time.
still hasn't, it's still the way.
Yeah, yeah, right. And so this forms, but in the process and this rise of evangelicalism because it is this sort of weird big tent, right of all these groups.
You lose some things.
You lose any kind of ecclesiology.
You lose any sense that there's a visible church, and there's a church with some kind of
visible boundaries that could be.
determined objectively, right? You lose that. You also lose the idea of any kind of unity in theology
because you've got to cross lines. You've got to include your Presbyterians and your dispensationalists.
You've got to include your pre-millennialists and your omelennilists. You've got to include
your people who baptize babies and people who don't, right? They've all got to be in this big tent,
which means all of those issues that are in any way controversial, right, have to get demoted to
second.
areas. Yeah, you can agree to disagree. Yes. And then arbitrary lines are drawn in terms
of what are the primary issues? What are the issues we have to agree on to be in the
tech? And it's why like when you see frankly, when you see Protestants arguing with each other
on the internet, and one of them calls the other one a heretic, there's no immediate basis
for understanding why they're using that word. Like on what basis is this one a heretic
This one isn't, you know, it's like you said,
just through the line on the seat,
in the back seat of the car,
it's that everyone on that side is a heretic, right?
This is the line.
They're going over, there's a heretic.
Yeah.
And more and more,
I have what I think is a good analogy for this.
You may have heard in political discussions,
people make the argument that like the founding documents
of the United States, the Constitution,
at all.
kind of only work if you have sort of a unified Christian culture.
Yeah, I mean, I think I think one of the early founding fathers said something like this
constitution is only for a Christian and moral people.
Yeah. Now regardless of what you think of that argument in terms of politically in the United
States, you may not even be in the United States as you listen to this and you may not care.
But I think that is true of what we see in Protestantism.
I think when you look at the first generation of the
for me.
things like solar scriptura, right? And things like the distinctions they're making
worked fine because you have broadly Christian people who had come out of Latin
chrysanthem. Right? And who had made some changes?
Christian? Yeah, but we're still within that envelope, still within that culture,
right? So yeah, yeah, if you push this whole theology in a version.
works righteousness, you can end up in a very antinomian place, right, where people don't
do good. But we all know Protestants who have a theology that seems to suggest they should
be like that, who nonetheless do a lot of charitable and good things.
Oh, I mean, like the kind that I was raised in, very firmly believed and taught explicitly,
like once you are genuinely saved and have that conversion experience, that you are going
to heaven no matter what you do after that.
one saved always saved. But none of them would also say, and that means you should not bother going to church.
None of them would say that they would never ever say that.
It's going to have a broadly Christian people steeped in Christian culture.
You can ideologically hold to those kind of ideas and not follow them out.
You can ideologically hold this holoscryptura and still as all the Reformers did believe in not only the doctrine of the Holy Trinity,
as they understood it and had received it in Latin theology, but
things like the perpetual virginity of the Theotokos
Which all the Reformers still held to go in
Right
Because they were just broadly Christian and in this Christian culture. There's no reason to doubt those things
Right, but when you don't have that anymore
When you don't have that understanding anymore and you just have the principle
simple, right? Only what can be shown in the scriptures,
in contravertively, or by good and necessary inference, and I'm
the judge of what is a good and necessary inference, it all
breaks down. It all starts to break down. Now the Trinity's
negotiable, right? I at a Protestant seminary that I won't
name suggested that if someone does not believe the contents of
that I see in creed, they're not a-
Christian and I was laughed at. They thought that was ridiculous. Not a couple people.
Everyone. I mean, this to me is why as long as we're throwing out somewhat spicy takes,
this to me is why this whole kind of the idea of the the the Ray Conquista of the of the
main line in the US is is is a doomed project.
Why you got it? Because it's because the kid looks like Marvin England from head of the
class. Really? And now you've got a dog in on this show. Yeah.
No, it's because it's like, okay, the idea is we want to turn the clock back and restore
these denominations to where they used to be.
They're like, well, how do you think they got where they are now?
It's not because someone came in and hijacked the whole nine yards.
It's because they developed into the direction that they were going.
As we, you know, as frankly, we've spent the last three hours showing.
Honestly.
So like, you know, if you can turn the clock back, I mean, that's nice, but like, just going to end up.
This is where it goes.
Very likely.
This is the problem with the whole thing we said at the beginning about the West.
Right.
You roll it back to right before the enlightenment. Guess what happens? The enlightenment again.
Yeah.
Okay.
All this quote unquote woke stuff. You hate that's Western culture and its final form.
And the only reason it's the final form is that it's about to collapse.
Yeah, which I mean...
I don't want people to get hurt or die or whatever, but I think that some collapse might
well be helpful.
Yeah.
So we've talked about how evangelicalism in particular, in prosimism in general has become
a mess.
And in some cases with evangelicalism only vaguely Christian.
And aerobic Catholic friends are probably a bit real.
Finally off the hook.
I got some bad news for you guys.
Dun dun dun.
Because Rome during this time has just gotten completely Protestantized.
And that's both in the US and Europe.
This is just, this happened.
I mean, again, I love my Roman Catholic friends.
I do have Roman Catholic friends.
I love them.
like the Roman Catholic services I have been to over the last
30 years, all of them frankly feel like kind of watered down Lutheran services. That's how
it gets up. And so, yeah, yeah, yeah. And, and, you know, like, it's weird. It seems like,
it seems like there's this at least in America, America thought Catholicism in terms of its
existential reality.
There's this kind of battle on the ground between like will a parish be like mainline Protestants or where they'd be like evangelical Protestants, you know, and then of course you've got, you know, charismatic Catholics, which is.
But the funny thing is, as long as we're being spicy, I guess, I've said this twice now.
You know, I always thought in the 80s and 90s when even
delacol were trying to make their own versions of rock and pop music,
especially when I became a...
and was doing, you know, especially in the summer,
is doing big concerts down at the arena and stuff.
I always felt like the pop in the rock
at the Evangelical Church that I went to was like,
eh, by comparison, I feel like the sort of either
mainliner or Evangelical or occasionally
charismatic stuff that the Catholics are doing
at their parishes is kind of eh, in comparison
to sort of the real versions of those things
that are in Protestantism.
Like I watched a video of charismatic Catholics.
I'm like
Come on, give me some real holy rollers here.
Like come on, give me some real pedicostles, like some people that mean it.
You know, um, but yeah, this is what you're saying.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, and we're not we're not here.
Look, we're not here talking about abuses.
No, no, this is no road.
Galician.
Entire of that.
Right.
Sanction by bishops.
I'm talking about the mainstream mainstream Roman Catholicism.
Yeah.
In the United States has been evangelicalized.
God bless some day.
go to the Novis Ordo. I know you don't want to go to the Novis Ordo. Okay. None of the
Roman Catholic apologists on YouTube go to the Novis Ordo. They all go to visit the right
churches. It's interesting. They're worth it. That is the case. Yeah. But go to the Novis
Ordo. Okay. Your hymnal has a mighty fortress in our is our God. I know that was amazing
to me. Like one of the last Catholic masses I went to I went with my I had a Catholic roommate
for a while and sometimes when he had an event or something.
something I would go with him, you know, because he was my friend. And I remember, you know,
pulling the hymnal out of the pew and kind of thumbing through it. And there was a mighty fortress,
but frankly, the world's most famous ex-calf like, I couldn't believe it. Amazing. Amazing.
The music is evangelical worship music now, right?
V, V. Yeah, you're so...
the Eucharist at every mass, but Lutherans do that too, so do Anglicans. It's just become
Protestantized. And it's not only become Protestantized in terms of the worship, but culturally
it's now being Protestantized because evangelicalism, that big tent we were talking about, part
of what has happened to keep the movement together since the late 70s.
and specifically the election of 1980,
a blame and Reagan for this in large part.
What is, since there isn't any shared theology holding
evangelicalism together anymore as a big tent, right?
There's no shared theology holding together.
There's no ecclesiology holding it together.
No structures, no ecclesial structures holding it together.
It's now held together by politics.
Yeah, I think that it's essential.
become a political movement now. And in the United States, noisorno-Roman Catholic
autism has basically joined that political movement, which is a very strange
bedfellow type situation, right? Because, you know, you've got, you've got a
Bible-pounded Baptist who say that the Roman Catholic Church is the whore of
Babylon, but who will?
Why enough to go vote for a Roman Catholic government representative?
Because they're pro-life and they've got an R after their name.
So the American Roman Catholic Church is very quickly just attaching itself.
And that's the better half.
the ones who have it just gone liberal and flanked, right?
We won't even talk about them because then we get into the abuses, right?
And we're not wanting to beat up on Roman Catholics with the abuses, honestly.
No, it's, it's, I know you're thinking that I'm talking about the best parts.
The best parts are problematic now.
And in Europe, it's frankly far worse.
Uh, in, in Europe, it's also been Protestantized, but it's European Protestantism, meaning it's been
and hagalized.
If that's-
That's not a word it is now.
Yeah, which probably explains a lot of the sort of the rainbow coalition gets a lot more
truck and a lot less resistance in European Catholicism than it does in American Catholicism.
Right.
And Newman, who was no liberal by much of any definition, but Newman with his development
of doctor hypothesis which he used to solve various problems played right into this.
I'm pretty sure thoroughly unintentionally, but played right into this because that was seized upon by our
Hangle friends and chief among our Hangle friends in this case for Erwin Cathales as of his Carl
Roder. So there's this phenomenon in Europe where anytime you have a philosopher who was
who is profound and respected, it makes some kind of impact.
philosophical world, you then get the teemothiology version of that philosopher. Shortly thereafter.
And the philosopher himself usually doesn't like him if he knows it.
It's like first you get the Beatles and then you have the monkeys. Except I have some respect
for the monkeys. I will admit there's some monkeys songs. Yes.
Still you have to admit there's a similar kind of relation
positive going on. Yeah. So, you know, Heidegger shows up, you get Rudolph
Boltman, right? Yeah. Yeah.
Hegel gives you Karl Ronder. And Karl Ronder, you made out of heard of, even if you're Roman
Catholic, you made out of, I've heard of him, unless you studied theology somewhere, specifically
modern Roman Catholic theology. He sometimes referred to as the Holy Ghost Writer of Vatican II.
Because he took this approach, which he called transcendental
Thomism. Wow. Because the victory of Thomas Aquinas
at Trent Met, no matter how far out your view is, you gotta
pretend you're a Thomas, right? So transcendental
Thomism, but which is basically Hegel, it is basically God
is unfolding.
knowledge of himself into the world, right? We grow things change. She sees us
upon Newman's yes, things develop, but that development now is not like Newman
argued like, you know, the Acorn becomes the oak tree, but everything that's in
the oak tree was present in the Acorn, it could be actual change. It can be
actual we know better now right so in this view
you what you have in the New Testament in St. Paul's writings is St. Paul's first
century view of these things. It is a stage in the evolution of the unfolding of
the knowledge of God, right? An important stage, right? But a stage of Spencer
past. So Rato will argue that the church now, by that.
he means the Roman Catholic Church, he means Rome.
That the Church of Rome now in itself understanding and its internal understanding understands
the mystery of Christ to better than Saint Paul.
Yeah.
Better than Saint Peter.
Okay.
And this is an ongoing process.
And the reason he's called that, these are the Vatican II, is that Vatican II really
enshrines his views.
Okay.
All the Roman Caliphos who hate Vatican II are
to hate Vatican II. It's a fundamental change, a fundamental European
Protestantization of your religion, okay? That's what it did, but I mean bad news for
you, you're not getting that repealed. Yeah, current mission of Rome has said
now's the time where we need to really implement Vatican II that is the
division. That's now where Rome.
is. Right? And those conservatives, even if now it's primarily a mix of political conservatives
and whatever in the US are viewed as a problem. Because they're associated by European Roman Catholics
with the fundamentalists. Right? The Protestant fundamentalists who opposed the more
illumine to Protestantism that came out of Europe.
Yeah.
Time fails.
Obviously there's a ton of stuff we left out.
Major figures we left out.
We didn't talk about the papacy.
We didn't talk about all kinds of elements.
You can't cover all of the history of Latin theology and what
episode, no matter how long I keep father Andrew up.
But we wanted to take...
this trajectory through it. And there are probably elements of this that we talked about
that we didn't talk about that will return to in future episodes inevitably. The show goes long
enough. But we wanted to go down this one trajectory, this one winding historical road, right,
to show this thread so we can make a particular contrast, right?
it. Liberalization the place where we ended up.
is the fruit of the tree. It's not this weird thing that's cut in. It's not this
foreign thing. It's not a hijacking. It is along this trajectory, right? That
Latin theology has taken, and this trajectory that accelerated after the
split with the East. And that
liberalization, that sense of development, that sense that, oh, now we understand it's
cool to have 16-year-old girls head out the Eucharist in a Roman Catholic Church.
Which is, I mean, they're called extraordinary Eucharistic ministers, but it's ordinary.
It's ordinary now.
It's completely normal.
The vast majority, at least in the US, the vast majority of Roman Catholics are not
receiving communion from a priest. They're receiving it from a layman.
often in one kind still. Can you imagine Thomas Aquinas let alone St. Augustine seeing that?
Yeah. Right. And unless your response to me is, well, of course not, they were sexist and didn't
understand God as well as we do, right? Then you're not on board with the program. They're going to
going to be drumming you out as soon as they can.
In contrast in the East and the Orthodox Church, right, everything is oriented toward preservationism
toward keeping things the way they are and keeping them alive.
And if you want to be like certain apologists online and say, well, they didn't really achieve the form, you have it in exactly until like the fifth century.
I'll give you that, right?
I'll give you fifth century church versus, you know, 21st century church.
any any daily which one do you want to be a part of?
Right?
It will just take Latin, right?
You offer me the choice.
Do I want to be a member of a of the Roman Catholic Church today or a
Protestant Church today or a member of St. Augustine Church in North Africa?
In the fifth century, I'm going to take his every day.
See the Gustens every day of the week, twice on Sunday, although I can't
receive the Eucharist twice on Sunday.
So, because I just hang around.
But you get the point, right? There is over time in Latin theology, redefinition, slippage, loss,
right? And it's not something you can just correct. It's not something where you can just roll back the clock.
I would love it if we could just go into the church of Rome
sweep things up, clean things up,
and come back into communion,
but it's not possible, I'm sorry.
It's not possible.
The things that would have to change
would dismantle it.
It would be what it is.
Same thing with any Protestant church, you name.
And so you end up with, right?
People need to just join the Orthodox church.
Yeah, I mean I think
I think that it's unbalanced a good thing that, you know, there are like official conversations
that go on between Orthodox and Protestants and Orthodox and Roman Catholics.
I don't like if, you know, some of them have the stated goal of restoring communion.
I don't think that that's going to happen.
I don't think that they can actually achieve that through...
I mean, there's these commissions and it seems pretty clear that even one of these commissions
puts out another agreed statement or whatever that literally no one follows it.
Like no one who's actually in charge, you know, signs it or anything like that.
But I still think it's good for the sake of friendship.
I think it's good for the sake of witnessing the Orthodox faith to non-Orth...
Orthodox people, you know, to show that we're open and that we care about people who are
another religious groups.
That said, when I, you know, like a lot of the work that I do is connecting with people
who are learning about the Orthodox Church for the first time, considering it for the first
time becoming orthodox, trying to convert, trying to tell other...
people about it. And overwhelmingly, the thing that people say that they're coming for is not
what you read in some media accounts. They're not coming because like, oh, here I know that my
political views will have a hearing or whatever. I'm sure there are people like that, but that is not
my experience. No, the thing that they keep saying over and over again,
women is that they're there because they want a deep spiritual life, which means that they're
not getting it somewhere else. And I think that when you have this recipe for change that we've
been discussing for the last three plus hours.
That what ends up happening is that
You don't actually have depth. You might have accumulated lots of stuff over the
centuries, but what you've accumulated ends up becoming this kind of moving target of confusion.
That's not consistent with itself. Right? And so you can't grasp onto that. And then on the other side,
you get the sort of non-accumulating groups, you know, the kinds of say, well history is bunk and
It doesn't matter any of that.
Believe in Jesus, trust Jesus, and you're good.
Then what you end up getting is something that's deeply that's deeply now that is very shallow
can be deeply shallow
and
Why would people become Orthodox Christians because they know?
From their experience not just because some apologists whoever told them they know from their experience that it's
It's gonna be the same
And we've
We've done whole episodes on this podcast about how the Orthodox Church changes, and that's
a very different kind of thing than what we've been talking about for this episode.
The ways that the Orthodox Church changes are not fundamental to its identity.
And so I think one of the reasons why many people are...
showing up at our doors and knocking on our doors, even though there has not been some big evangelistic push that we've been all working on together,
is a sense that the changing of the world, and on many of the changes that have been brought, particularly by a lot of the stuff that happened in the Protestant Reformation,
really picked up then, and then it feels like it's accelerating now, you know, that this, it feels like society is collapsing,
And, you know, I don't know what that means exactly.
You can have different levels.
of collapse and different kinds of collapse.
Claps doesn't necessarily mean we're going to have civil war or anything like that or
big financial crisis.
Oh, you know, who knows?
I don't know about those things.
I don't know how to predict those things.
But I think that there is definitely a collapse of the sense of the narrative of our culture,
a collapse of the sense of what we are together.
And the feeling that this has been accelerating, especially over the last five years.
particularly five, six years. I think is what led a lot of people to say,
hold on a second. I want to be part of the story that is the story.
And I know that probably in the days and weeks that followed this episode,
getting published, there probably some people that will listen to it.
And they probably will not get to this point of the episode.
and it'll be, you know, quite unhappy.
But I think I hope that whatever unhappiness they might have and listening to some of these criticisms that we've leveled
will at least make them think for a moment about whether or not they might be true.
If they don't think they're true, I mean I pray that they are as faithful to God as they can be wherever it is that they are.
But if they might be true, I think it's worth looking into.
And it's very worth looking into what it is that the Orthodox Church truly is.
It is not a community, a community, a community of perfect people.
It's not a community of perfect church leaders.
We got to, we got as, you know, as many failures as anybody else in terms of who we are as persons.
But it has definitely a different mentality about what it means for the church to soldier in this world.
And so, you know, 12.
of you who are escaping the confusion and the chaos and the the weirdness and coming to the
Orthodox Church. How have you got here? Welcome. Welcome home and dig in because this is the place to be.
So aside from blackpilling everyone.
what Latin theology and it's lack of a future. I want to make clear, you know, as we went
through this, this sort of genealogy, and I hope in vain, I know it's in vain, that people
won't actually take it as Father Andrew said, as criticisms, but take it as descriptive.
So what I was trying to do, right, to be descriptive of currents and cross currents and things.
and is explanatory sort of how we got here.
Cause I don't, I don't mean a lot of Roman Catholic people
who say, I'm super happy with the way
the Roman Catholic church is going.
And I live in a 70% Roman Catholic area.
So I meet some tribes who reminds me of the movie Gladiator.
They believe in the dream that was once held
a place called Rome. Right, they they...
There is this thing that they believe in.
There is this thing.
But they probably most of all people are painfully aware
that it doesn't correspond to the day-to-day reality.
And that's why they try to find,
they try to find their Latin mass,
they try to find their trad parish,
they try to find, they go to a Byzantine-right parish,
right, something, but those places are getting closed
down, let's be honest, that they're their, they're, they're the enemy as far as their
hierarchy is concerned. I don't run into Protestants, right? Whether we're talking about
confessional Protestants of whom I know a fair number from my seminary days and beyond.
I don't know like a vegetable
Protestants who are looking around.
I don't know what he says online, but I bet you've got Jordan Cooper, got a couple beers in him. He admit that the prospects of American Lutheranism and the current scene is not filling him with hope.
uh the uh the uh evangelical scene uh i know people who are fired up politically
on the evangelical scene uh i i you know and some of them are fired
in a particular church plant, but that church plant is usually the fifth or sixth church plant.
They've been a part of, and that's sort of their pattern is just going to do church plants
getting fired up and when the fire dies down, they bolt. I just, I don't know anybody who looks
out at the Protestant or evangelical or Roman Catholic religious scene today and is filled with
positivity about it thinks it's in a good place and I have to be honest with you.
I can honestly say that when I look at the Orthodox Church today, I can be happy to think
it's in a good place. That doesn't mean it's perfect, right? We have problems. We got all kinds of
problems, right? We got scandals too. Our scandals are dealt with a little differently than some of
the scandals in other parts, in other, the other communities, but we have them. We have flaws. But the
flaws we have, the problems we have, the difficulties we have, are the flaws and difficulties that the
the church is faced in every generation forever.
They're not.
new problems. There are problems that result from an abandonment of core Christian teachings.
They're not problems that result from having lost elements of traditional Christian practice.
People who are fervent and traditional about the Orthodox faith are not considered the enemy
by the hierarchy of the Orthodox Church. They may want to reign in their zeal once in a while.
They're not the enemy.
They're trying to drive them out of the church
for being traditional, right?
Or conservative, right?
That's not a thing in the Orthodox church.
So again, I'm not trying to be critical,
trying to be descriptive.
And all of this is aimed at the movements,
not the individuals, right?
St. Augustine is a saint.
But Thomas Aquinas was a good man. He was a good man. He was a godly man. He was trying to follow God.
He was a brilliant man who was trying to follow God. That's not just Father Steven D. Young going
off the reservation, okay? Read the early Orthodox responses with Orthodox bishops,
red Thomas Aquinas. You know what they say about him? They say if only he had
born here instead of in the West.
They said think of what he could have done if he had been born here with that mind.
And that desire to serve God, if he hadn't been burned with things like the
Filiokue and these other doctrines, right?
If he hadn't had to work within the framework of 13th century Latin theology,
think of how glorious that could have been.
That's there is no negative statement in there about Thomas Aquinas as a person.
None. Right. So this is not about, I mean, there are a couple people we've named Charles
Finney. I have some issues with, right? Carl Rader. Hegel seems like an interesting cat.
I don't know. I might have a beer with it. Kant boring his heck. But this isn't about
people and this isn't about if you're listening to this, this isn't about you. Okay. When I talk
about you would
Evangelism becoming a political movement more than a religious movement. I'm not criticizing you
Right, I'm trying hopefully to give you some clarity about what's happening around you
What's going on at your church?
What's going on with the culture of your church? What's going on with the way
Christ is talked about by political figures today in the United States
If you're a Roman Catholic, I'm not here to criticize you or put you down, right?
Again, I'm trying to be descriptive.
and say, hey, where did this come from?
Why are these things happening in your parish?
Why are people leaving your parish?
Right?
Why did your bishop get fired if you live
across the border in Texas?
What's happening?
One of these things I'm hearing from Europe
coming out of the Vatican, right?
How does this all fit together?
How does this make sense?
That's what I hope we did with this episode.
This was not, I'm gonna say a bunch of bad things
Bye.
your church and then tell you you need to join mine because mine's better. Okay? This is us trying to
describe what's happening to you. Hopefully give you some clarity and some understanding. So things
to think about and then say there's a safe haven from all of that here in the Orthodox church.
Doesn't mean your life's gonna be easy, right? What's becoming Orthodox Christian and really devote
yourself to the Christian life? That's when the hard part begins, right? But the difficulties will
will be the difficult.
of working out your salvation.
Not the difficulty of reconciling bad theology,
not the difficulty of being persecuted by your own bishop,
not the difficulty of hearing political rally speeches instead
of a sermon, not the inability to get basic doctrinal questions answered.
Right. It's going to be a different kind of difficult,
and a kind of difficult that's salvific that makes people holy.
right and lead some to the kingdom of God. So dress all your hate mail to father Andrew and
that makes you fit.
Well, thank you very much everyone for tuning in.
That's our show for tonight.
If you didn't happen to get us on the phone live, you can still get in touch with us.
You can email us at LordofSpiritsandAncientFate.com.
You can send a message to our Facebook page.
You can also leave us a voice mail at SpeakPipe.com slash LordofSpirits.
If you have basic questions,
about Orthodox Christianity or you need help to find a parish to live that life. The father
was just talking about go to orthodoxintro.org.
And join us for our live broadcast of the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 6 p.m.
Eastern 3 p.m. Pacific, 47 deadbeats living in the backstreet, northeast west south, all
in the same house.
If you're on Facebook, you can follow our page. You can also join our discussion group
and leave ratings and reviews so that other people can see them and share this
So directly with a friend who you know is going to love it.
And probably be sure to go to achromate.com
stroke support and help make sure we and lots of other AFR
podcasters stay on the air sitting in a back room waiting for
the big boom. I'm in a bedroom waiting for my baby.
Thank you. Good night and God bless you.
You've been listening to the Lord of spirits with Orthodox
Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen, Daymak and Father
a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels
round about the throne and the beasts and the elders.
And the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000
and thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice,
worthy is the land that was slain to receive power
and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory
and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11-13.